<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Oliver&apos;s Blog</title>
        <description>My own small private space in the world of bewitched madness!</description>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
        <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 09:54:36 +0200</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 09:54:36 +0200</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.3.3</generator>
        
            <item>
                <title>Arq Backup - a versatile solution to back up your files on Mac and Windows</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;backups-are-essential-for-any-use-case-and-while-there-are-many-solutions-on-the-market-some-apps-stand-out-for-their-level-of-flexibility-time-machine-on-the-mac-already-does-a-great-job-but-is-limited-to-connected-drives---so-how-do-you-back-up-on-the-move-enter-arq-backup&quot;&gt;Backups are essential for any use case and while there are many solutions on the market, some apps stand out for their level of flexibility. Time Machine on the Mac already does a great job, but is limited to connected drives - so how do you back up on the move? Enter, Arq Backup!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travelling with your important data doesn’t have to mean skipping backups or combining them with a device you’re already carrying - just imagine if all your luggage got stolen or lost. Although Apple’s built-in Time Machine works well with connected USB drives or via SMB shares when you are at home, there is an obvious gap when you are on the move. Filling this gap is the task of Arq Backup which is available for Windows and Mac, but as a long-time Mac user I will focus on the latter edition of the application, created by Haystack Software LLC and founder Stefan Reitshamer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are many solutions and software formerly known as “personal firewalls”, especially in the Windows genre, my preferred macOS actually comes just with a simple and basic firewall on board: “Keeps things out” as a first point of defense but lacks a certain granularity in terms of detailed configuration options to specifically choose which services or data can be transferred from (!) the inside to the World Wide Web. Solutions like Objective-See’s &lt;a href=&quot;../LuLu-Yet-another-powerful-firewall-for-your-Mac/&quot;&gt;LuLu&lt;/a&gt; are great options in the Open Source-genre while &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.obdev.at/products/littlesnitch/index-de.html&quot;&gt;Objective Development’s Little Snitch&lt;/a&gt; (enter, version 6!) is a paid alternative that has been with me for many years now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/arqbackup_targets.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Snitch 6 Network Monitor&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;welcome-little-snitch-6&quot;&gt;Welcome, Little Snitch 6!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, Little Snitch has not only been with me for many years but also with many Mac users who can look back on 20 years of history. As I mentioned above, there are many solutions out there that try to make your Mac more private and Little Snitch is one of them, with the aforementioned history. Basically, it sniffs („snitches!“ the network traffic on all your connected devices and either allows, denies or warns about traffic initiated by software installed on the Mac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My use case has always been “deny all” in terms of incoming (of course) and outgoing traffic. For me, the way Little Snitch works is that once it is deployed and allowed to sniff the traffic, it alerts me on every connection that any kind of software or service initiates and lets me choose what actions to take for that specific request: For example, a local application that just needs to check for updates can be regulated to use only a specific host and port 443 (TCP) for SSL traffic so that it can check whether an update is available or not. No more, no less - and tracking apps that try to ‘phone home’ for whatever reason may become a relic of the past with Little Snitch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/little_snitch_6_connections_list.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Checking the connections in Little Snitch 6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new version comes with some new features like DNS-encryption, a convenient access to blocklists, an optically revamped traffic chart, a more versatile control center in macOS’ menu bar or even sound notifications in case an app hits Little Snitch initial software firewall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-new-features-in-detail&quot;&gt;The new features in detail&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DNS encryption: As long as your provider does this or you are using one of the DNS-encrypted nameservers out there, everything is fine. If this isn’t the case, Little Snitch 6 also offers the option to add custom name servers to suit specific needs or to avoid the more famous DNS servers out there&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrated blocklists: Users can easily select from a curated list of blocklists and install them with a single click to add an extra layer of protection against unwanted connections&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New control center on the menu bar: Get quick, at-a-glance access to key network information, recent activity graphs and recently blocked connections right at the top of your screen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Usage statistics: Track and optimize your firewall rules based on usage frequency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enhanced web application support: Gain better and more granular control over external connections initiated by web pages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improved firewall rules: Use cryptographic code signing identifiers for better process identification, resistant to application renaming or moving&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and many more!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/little_snitch_6_rules_window.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Rules Window&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the initial installation (and assuming you choose the “Alert” mode first), Little Snitch will nag you with lots of notifications about background services or initiated connections and as you open each additional application, the basic ruleset will grow to provide a solid foundation for your specific use case on MacOS and the traffic happening from your machine. This ruleset can of course be modified, deleted or enriched with additional blocklists that many users will already be familiar with (Peter Lowe’s, Ad Away or URLhaus to name a few - adding custom ones is also possible!), so securing your Mac’s outgoing traffic is a simple process, even when you’re on the go, and this process has become even easier with the new features of Little Snitch 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/little_snitch_6_menu_bar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Snitch 6 in macOS’ menu bar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, it’s up to you whether you need a product like Little Snitch or not. If you don’t care which packets leave your machine in which direction - fine. But if you do and you want to regulate them or just see what’s happening to them, this one might be of particular interest to you. Little Snitch doesn’t use too many system resources, and the utility itself only uses 0.7% of the CPU when doing its usual work - so there’s no compromise between security, resources and visual usability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using Little Snitch for years and it quickly became my daily driver on all the Macs I’ve owned over the years - and once it’s learned its initial set of rules, it rarely pops out of the background so you won’t even know it’s there unless it says „Hello!“: There are no distractions at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pricing-and-availability&quot;&gt;Pricing and availability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of writing, Arq Backup 7 is the latest iteration and is available for macOS (version 7.26.10) and Windows (version 7.27.8.0) with a 30-day trial. The standard version costs $49.99 when first purchased, with renewal at $25.00 per year for a single computer. Arq Premium includes five computers and 1 TB of included storage plus web access to backups for $59.99/year. For the latter, the storage location can be selected from three locations in the US, Finland, Belgium, the Netherlands, Singapore or Taiwan to meet specific, GDPR-compliant needs and regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arq Backup can be downloaded from the official website &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.arqbackup.com/download/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/arq-backup-a-versatile-solution-to-back-up-your-files-on-mac-and-windows/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/arq-backup-a-versatile-solution-to-back-up-your-files-on-mac-and-windows/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                <category>apple</category>
                
                <category>mac</category>
                
                <category>windows</category>
                
                <category>arq</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Little Snitch 6 released, taking Mac-privacy to the next level</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;four-years-ago-i-blogged-about-little-snitch-5-a-software-firewall-like-product-from-austrian-company-objective-development-which-successfully-made-the-transition-to-macos-11-big-sur-now-little-snitch-6-has-been-released-and-continues-to-be-an-important-building-block-in-the-security-strategy-of-privacy-conscious-users&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../Little-Snitch5-makes-the-successful-switch-to-macOS-11-Big-Sur/&quot;&gt;Four years ago I blogged about Little Snitch 5&lt;/a&gt;, a software firewall-like product from Austrian company Objective Development, which successfully made the transition to MacOS 11 Big Sur. Now Little Snitch 6 has been released and continues to be an important building block in the security strategy of privacy-conscious users.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether on Windows, Mac or Linux, using a particular operating system is always a matter of trust. Some people don’t care at all, some prefer to avoid the big tech vendors, and some even want to use the system they personally prefer with an extra pinch of salt, controlling exactly what kind of communication leaves the specific machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are many solutions and software formerly known as “personal firewalls”, especially in the Windows genre, my preferred macOS actually comes just with a simple and basic firewall on board: “Keeps things out” as a first point of defense but lacks a certain granularity in terms of detailed configuration options to specifically choose which services or data can be transferred from (!) the inside to the World Wide Web. Solutions like Objective-See’s &lt;a href=&quot;../LuLu-Yet-another-powerful-firewall-for-your-Mac/&quot;&gt;LuLu&lt;/a&gt; are great options in the Open Source-genre while &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.obdev.at/products/littlesnitch/index-de.html&quot;&gt;Objective Development’s Little Snitch&lt;/a&gt; (enter, version 6!) is a paid alternative that has been with me for many years now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/little_snitch_6_network_monitor.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Snitch 6 Network Monitor&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;welcome-little-snitch-6&quot;&gt;Welcome, Little Snitch 6!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, Little Snitch has not only been with me for many years but also with many Mac users who can look back on 20 years of history. As I mentioned above, there are many solutions out there that try to make your Mac more private and Little Snitch is one of them, with the aforementioned history. Basically, it sniffs („snitches!“ the network traffic on all your connected devices and either allows, denies or warns about traffic initiated by software installed on the Mac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My use case has always been “deny all” in terms of incoming (of course) and outgoing traffic. For me, the way Little Snitch works is that once it is deployed and allowed to sniff the traffic, it alerts me on every connection that any kind of software or service initiates and lets me choose what actions to take for that specific request: For example, a local application that just needs to check for updates can be regulated to use only a specific host and port 443 (TCP) for SSL traffic so that it can check whether an update is available or not. No more, no less - and tracking apps that try to ‘phone home’ for whatever reason may become a relic of the past with Little Snitch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/little_snitch_6_connections_list.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Checking the connections in Little Snitch 6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new version comes with some new features like DNS-encryption, a convenient access to blocklists, an optically revamped traffic chart, a more versatile control center in macOS’ menu bar or even sound notifications in case an app hits Little Snitch initial software firewall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-new-features-in-detail&quot;&gt;The new features in detail&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DNS encryption: As long as your provider does this or you are using one of the DNS-encrypted nameservers out there, everything is fine. If this isn’t the case, Little Snitch 6 also offers the option to add custom name servers to suit specific needs or to avoid the more famous DNS servers out there&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integrated blocklists: Users can easily select from a curated list of blocklists and install them with a single click to add an extra layer of protection against unwanted connections&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New control center on the menu bar: Get quick, at-a-glance access to key network information, recent activity graphs and recently blocked connections right at the top of your screen&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Usage statistics: Track and optimize your firewall rules based on usage frequency&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enhanced web application support: Gain better and more granular control over external connections initiated by web pages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improved firewall rules: Use cryptographic code signing identifiers for better process identification, resistant to application renaming or moving&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and many more!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/little_snitch_6_rules_window.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Rules Window&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the initial installation (and assuming you choose the “Alert” mode first), Little Snitch will nag you with lots of notifications about background services or initiated connections and as you open each additional application, the basic ruleset will grow to provide a solid foundation for your specific use case on MacOS and the traffic happening from your machine. This ruleset can of course be modified, deleted or enriched with additional blocklists that many users will already be familiar with (Peter Lowe’s, Ad Away or URLhaus to name a few - adding custom ones is also possible!), so securing your Mac’s outgoing traffic is a simple process, even when you’re on the go, and this process has become even easier with the new features of Little Snitch 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/little_snitch_6_menu_bar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Snitch 6 in macOS’ menu bar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, it’s up to you whether you need a product like Little Snitch or not. If you don’t care which packets leave your machine in which direction - fine. But if you do and you want to regulate them or just see what’s happening to them, this one might be of particular interest to you. Little Snitch doesn’t use too many system resources, and the utility itself only uses 0.7% of the CPU when doing its usual work - so there’s no compromise between security, resources and visual usability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using Little Snitch for years and it quickly became my daily driver on all the Macs I’ve owned over the years - and once it’s learned its initial set of rules, it rarely pops out of the background so you won’t even know it’s there unless it says „Hello!“: There are no distractions at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pricing-and-availability&quot;&gt;Pricing and availability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little Snitch 6 is available now for $59 or €59 per single-user license. Existing users can upgrade at a discounted price starting at $39 or €39. Licenses purchased after January 1st, 2024 will be valid for Little Snitch 6 at no additional cost while a free demo mode is also included, providing full functionality for three hours per session and can be reactivated as often as desired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little Snitch 6 is built for and supports MacOS 14 “Sonoma” and later. For more information and to purchase Little Snitch 6, just visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://obdev.at/&quot;&gt;Objective Development’s website&lt;/a&gt; to gather more information on the latest release.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/little-snitch-6-released-taking-mac-privacy-to-the-next-level/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/little-snitch-6-released-taking-mac-privacy-to-the-next-level/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                <category>apple</category>
                
                <category>mac</category>
                
                <category>littlesnitch</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>How to skip the ChatGPT for Mac waiting list and get access now</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-month-openai-has-released-the-native-chatgpt-app-for-macos-alongside-gpt-4o-anyone-can-install-this-app-yet-but-your-account-will-still-need-early-access-if-you-already-want-to-use-chatgpt-on-the-mac-desktop---but-there-is-a-workaround&quot;&gt;This month, OpenAI has &lt;a href=&quot;https://openai.com/index/gpt-4o-and-more-tools-to-chatgpt-free/&quot;&gt;released the native ChatGPT-app for macOS alongside GPT-4o&lt;/a&gt;. Anyone can install this app yet but your account will still need early access if you already want to use ChatGPT on the Mac-desktop - but there is a workaround!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, OpenAI &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.openai.com/en/articles/9275200-using-the-chatgpt-macos-app&quot;&gt;shared&lt;/a&gt; the status quo that the macOS-app is limited to “Plus and Team users” and that it will be rolling out more widely „in the coming weeks.“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have rolled out the macOS app to Plus and Team users, and we will make it more broadly available in the coming weeks. We also plan to launch a Windows version later this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/chat_gpt_mac_no_subscription.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;No use without subscription!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who have already managed to get their hands on the app without a subscription, the experience should look like the picture above after logging in. If you are interested in getting the app and perhaps using a small workaround to get it now despite having an active subscription, read on!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-the-app&quot;&gt;Getting the app&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have one of these subscriptions, you can (of course) download the app instantly by logging into ChatGPT on the web, clicking on your profile icon in the top right corner and then selecting “Download the App”. It’s as simple as that! If you don’t have a subscription and your Mac meets the requirements (at least an Apple Silicon based on Apple’s M1 SoC and the latest MacOS 14 “Sonoma”), check out the official &lt;a href=&quot;https://community.openai.com/t/downloading-the-new-desktop-app-for-chatgpt/746857&quot;&gt;thread&lt;/a&gt; or use &lt;a href=&quot;https://persistent.oaistatic.com/sidekick/public/ChatGPT_Desktop_public_latest.dmg&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; link to download the official .DMG file. Drag and drop it into your „Applications“-folder and you are ready to go, too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/chatgpt_mac_install_dmg.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Just drag and drop!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-skip-the-waitlist&quot;&gt;How to skip the waitlist&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally discovered and shared by &lt;a href=&quot;https://x.com/diegojimenez/status/1793287205542076524&quot;&gt;Diego Jimenez&lt;/a&gt; the workaround to skip the waitlist looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open ChatGPT for Mac and login&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Quit the app after the window size changes but before the login error appears (use Command+Q for more speed here)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Relaunch the app and discover it should be working&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/chatgpt_macos_open.png&quot; alt=&quot;ChatGPT without subscription on a Mac&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may take a turn or two to catch the right moment but after this procedure, even basic users without a subscription will now be able to use ChatGPT for Mac. We don’t know how long this workaround will last so if you’re interested in using the Mac desktop-client without a paid plan, hurry up!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 26 May 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/how-to-skip-the-chatgpt-for-mac-waiting-list-and-get-access-now/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/how-to-skip-the-chatgpt-for-mac-waiting-list-and-get-access-now/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>ai</category>
                
                <category>chatgpt</category>
                
                <category>mac</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>VMware kills Players, makes Pro free for personal use</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;while-broadcom-still-does-broadcom-things-after-acquiring-vmware-and-turning-pricing-and-portals-upside-down-at-least-the-question-what-happens-with-the-desktop-products-seems-to-have-been-answered&quot;&gt;While Broadcom still does Broadcom-things after acquiring VMware and turning pricing and portals upside down, at least the question what happens with the Desktop-products seems to have been answered.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Roy, product line manager for desktop hypervisor products such as VMware Fusion and Workstation, may already be familiar to users of these products. Now he has [blogged] (https://blogs.vmware.com/teamfusion/2024/05/fusion-pro-now-available-free-for-personal-use.html) about the latest state of VMware Workstation and Fusion after the acquisition. While rumors were already circulating that the entire desktop division would be sold anyway, the blog post seems to clarify that the Desktop hypervisors will remain despite Broadcom’s decision to kill off the popular “Player” editions no matter what.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;„Our goal with these changes has been to simplify how we bring VMware Desktop Hypervisor apps to market, while maintaining our support of the broader community of VMware Workstation and Fusion users of both free and paid products. So let’s dig into this simplification and more importantly, what this means to you as customers.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most significant part of this statement is that Fusion Pro and Workstation Pro will now have two licensing models. Broadcom now offers a “free personal use” or a “paid commercial use“-subscription for these applications. Depending on their specific use cases, users can now decide which license model is right for them: Anyone using the software for work on Windows, Mac or Linux will need a commercial edition, as was the case in the “VMware“-days before Broadcom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the specific Pro-installer-files provides all options letting the user decide which edition to use, the „lesser counterparts“ named VMware Workstation Player and VMware Fusion Player have been officially discontinued. Everyday users who need to create a virtual lab on their Mac, Windows or Linux computer can do so for free simply by registering and downloading the specific installers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/fusion-pro-personal-screen.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;VMware Fusion&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;goodbye-players&quot;&gt;Goodbye, Players!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users with Fusion Player Personal Licences can simply update to Fusion 13.5.2 and delete their specific licence key. Updating to 13.5.2 is mandatory here, but removing the existing player key will unlock the full “Pro for Personal Use” licence without the need for any additional keys. The whole process is described in a simple KB that describes what needs to be done at https://knowledge.broadcom.com/external/article?articleNumber=367660.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with Workstation Player for Windows and Linux, Workstation Pro requires a new download and installation but is licensed for personal use by default. Users will need a customer account at &lt;a href=&quot;support.broadcom.com&quot;&gt;support.broadcom.com&lt;/a&gt; to access the downloads as described below. Fusion Player 13 and Workstation Player 17 commercial licence customers will continue to see their products work and no new licence keys will be required to continue using these versions. According to Roy, once active support has expired, customers are encouraged to upgrade to the Pro version of these products for continued support and updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the new commercial model, VMware has also reduced its product line offerings to a single SKU for users requiring commercial licensing, eliminating more than 40 other SKUs and making it easier than ever to quote and purchase VMware Desktop Hypervisor-applications, Fusion Pro and Workstation Pro in the Enterprise. Subscriptions can be purchased from any Broadcom Advantage Partner or Digital River, which many users may be familiar with from reselling licences for other products. The VMware Desktop Hypervisor subscription is priced at $120/year and can also be purchased from the new [online store] (https://store.cloudvista.com).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/player-pro-transition.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Transitioning from Player to Pro&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-get-the-personal-use-editions&quot;&gt;How to get the personal use-editions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way to download the current version of VMware Workstation or Fusion for Personal Use is pretty straightforward once you have access to an an either migrated or freshly created account at Broadcom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Register for an account at &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.broadcom.com&quot;&gt;https://support.broadcom.com&lt;/a&gt; or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Login to an existing one&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Search for your specific edition of the personal edition by using one of these links (&lt;a href=&quot;https://support.broadcom.com/group/ecx/productdownloads?subfamily=VMware%20Fusion&quot;&gt;Fusion&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.broadcom.com/group/ecx/productdownloads?subfamily=VMware%20Workstation%20Pro&quot;&gt;Workstation&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download the corresponding edition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install the software and opt in for the „personal use license“ instead of entering a key for commercial use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/fusion_personal_edition.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Enabling the personal edition&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from all the hullabaloo surrounding Broadcom’s acquisition of VMware and the downsides in terms of stripped down editions and new pricing, this move was rather unexpected and will at least satisfy people who used the (now discontinued) Player. It also seems to put an end to the uncertain status quo of being able to download any update to Fusion or Workstation, but this may just be a drop in the ocean of a VMware in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, after all, let’s enjoy this lump of sugar as long as possible!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/vmware-kills-players-makes-pro-free-for-personal-use/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/vmware-kills-players-makes-pro-free-for-personal-use/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>vmware</category>
                
                <category>broadcom</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Tusks - Make posting to Mastodon feel like posting to a blog</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;sometimes-i-come-across-apps-that-i-would-never-have-missed-apps-that-come-out-of-nowhere-and-still-find-their-niche---tusks-by-developer-bardi-golriz-is-one-of-them-aiming-for-a-new-focus-when-posting-on-mastodon&quot;&gt;Sometimes I come across apps that I would never have missed. Apps that come out of nowhere and still find their niche - Tusks by developer &lt;a href=&quot;https://mas.to/@bardi&quot;&gt;Bardi Golriz&lt;/a&gt; is one of them, aiming for a new focus when posting on Mastodon.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although there are many Mastodon clients out there including my beloved &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/de/app/ivory-for-mastodon-by-tapbots/id6444602274&quot;&gt;Ivory&lt;/a&gt;, Tusks is not intended to replace them. Instead, this clean and slim app tries to complement existing clients by simply focusing on different tasks than the typical “post-a-picture-or-video-stuff-paired-with-some-text“-scenario we know from Social Media these days. &lt;a href=&quot;https://thirdculture.app/tusks&quot;&gt;Tusks&lt;/a&gt; gets rid of the timeline and just shows you your own posts, helping you to focus and build a thread-like experience while keeping everything in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-tusks-works&quot;&gt;How Tusks works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting a new thread in Tusks is as easy as making a single post but that’s not what makes it special. Tusks actively discourages posting into a vacuum and losing valuable context - this state is achieved by making it effortless to continue threading narratives. Each post becomes an update to a larger story that we can tell. Tusks is clearly aimed at pure writing but also supports the posting of images, including content warnings, and is aimed at people who blog, post or simply want to write more without distraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/tusks_composer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Composing with Tusks!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tusks shows posts as well as any replies to the original post but users won’t see replies or interactions with others. The app also comes with several features to help you organize and publish such as pinning threads for quick access, ignoring irrelevant posts when searching, or writing as much as possible on the go while Tusks breaks everything down into individual posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/tusks_context_menu.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tusks context menu&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app is currently free and can be downloaded from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/gb/app/tusks-make-mastodon-your-blog/id6473683937&quot;&gt;App Store&lt;/a&gt;. This free version is read-only and requires an update to Tusks Pro for posting and publishing which currently costs $4.99 / €5.99 for the first thousand fans and early adopters. Indie developer &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:bardi.golriz@gmail.com&quot;&gt;Bardi Golriz&lt;/a&gt; also says that the app will have a more expensive LTD (at least $9.99) and possibly a subscription option after the first thousand slots are filled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/tusks_ipad_inbox.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tusk’s iPad Inbox&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-client-client-replacement-or-&quot;&gt;New client, client replacement or… ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, Tusks is indeed no replacement for any of our standard Mastodon-apps but that’s not the intention here. Indeed  it puts even more value on Mastodon in case you meet the criteria the app was made for - focus, blogging, thread-based tooting. Although the current release is the initial one, the app’s quality is already very fine and stable on all platforms while the &lt;a href=&quot;https://midnight-beanie-ccb.notion.site/281be94b75504b60b600eb73ee1072f9?v=9479d0e4e1e8468187a7e2efbe3a53c7&quot;&gt;official roadmap&lt;/a&gt; already covers even more promising potential like editing posts, drag and drop, multi-account support or even scheduling posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are more of a blogger than a „tootist“ and have struggled with splitting posts into threads (a nightmare if you need to do it manually), you should definitely check out Tusks - you may not have missed it before, but it will certainly improve your tooting experience. It also helps to focus on the essential aspects of working with Mastodon and the topics people like to write about, and in my case, it definitely drives me to automatically work on longer articles that Tusks will publish in the future!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/tusks-make-posting-to-mastodon-feel-like-posting-to-a-blog/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/tusks-make-posting-to-mastodon-feel-like-posting-to-a-blog/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>tusks</category>
                
                <category>mastodon</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                <category>socialnetwork</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Bitwarden launches new MFA authenticator-app</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-use-of-a-second-factor-to-secure-online-accounts-has-become-a-must-over-time-long-before-the-triumph-of-passkeys-although-there-are-already-plenty-of-mobile-apps-that-generate-the-multi-factor-bitwarden-has-decided-to-create-its-own---and-it-has-a-pretty-interesting-roadmap&quot;&gt;The use of a second factor to secure online accounts has become a must over time, long before the triumph of passkeys. Although there are already plenty of mobile apps that generate the multi-factor, Bitwarden has decided to create its own - and it has a pretty interesting roadmap!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, the history of the (more or less) complex password has been a special one and after multi-factor authentication found its way to users, using an application to enter a generated number (the multi-factor) in addition to the password itself was the way to go. Over the years, security approaches have changed and hardware keys and passkeys have been added to the security layer but the first line of defense after a strong and complex password (and the least people can do to secure their accounts) are these randomly generated numbers from password managers or (even better) standalone apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of having at least a second factor at hand was recently demonstrated &lt;a href=&quot;https://pifferi.info/apple-locks-users-out-of-their-apple-ids-without-explanation/&quot;&gt;by the unexpected reset of my Apple ID-connected devices&lt;/a&gt; which forced me to update my password - I was worried, but definitely less worried because 2FA was already enabled in its most extreme iteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/towfiqu-barbhuiya-FnA5pAzqhMM-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Security first!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Bitwarden has &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitwarden.com/blog/bitwarden-just-launched-a-new-authenticator-app-heres-what-it-means-to-users/&quot;&gt;officially released&lt;/a&gt; a new multi-factor authentication app available for &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/bitwarden-authenticator/id6497335175&quot;&gt;iOS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.bitwarden.authenticator&quot;&gt;Android&lt;/a&gt;. It features the familiar TOTP (time-based one-time passwords) and can be used for accounts by scanning a QR code or manually entering the initial setup key, providing the familiar extra layer of authentication. Bitwarden, being an Open Source project, also provides the code for both apps in public GitHub repositories, separated into Android (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitwarden/authenticator-android&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) and iOS (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitwarden/authenticator-ios&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;„Bitwarden Authenticator provides immediate value to the Bitwarden user base who has been asking for a standalone app for several years. Stay tuned for upcoming new features that will help enterprise organizations enforce security policies to protect and monitor authentication to business applications.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Kyle Spearrin, founder and CTO of Bitwarden)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/bitwarden_authenicator_setup01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First setup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the TOTP feature was already implemented in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitwarden.com&quot;&gt;Bitwarden Password Manager&lt;/a&gt;, it was a premium add-on only available to paying customers or those using a self-hosted derivative called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dani-garcia/vaultwarden&quot;&gt;Vaultwarden&lt;/a&gt;. So speaking (and assuming this feature is still of interest to users), people can now stay within the “Bitwarden” brand and use the official authenticator, whether they’re paying customers or not. For example, if someone is new to Bitwarden, they can start with this standalone application without having to use Bitwarden’s password vault features, as these applications are (still) separate. From a security perspective, the second factor should usually be separated from the password manager itself, so running both apps could also be an improvement for current users and their own security layer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/bitwarden_authenicator_setup02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Continued setup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding new accounts is pretty straightforward, either by scanning the QR code or entering the token for the service you want to enable 2FA for. Bitwarden also revealed a guided roadmap with this first release in Phase 1 and not much else to do besides enabling 2FA or exporting the entries in it to a .json-backup file. There is no real backup yet, instead the phone backup will take care of backing up the data stored in the authenticator. An import option is said to be coming soon, and Authenticator codes synchronized with a Bitwarden account are features already announced for Phase 2. Phase 3 will bring push-based 2FA and account recovery as additional features while the final phase will target employee authentication and further &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitwarden.com/help/policies/&quot;&gt;security polices&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/bitwarden_authenticator_roadmap.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bitwarden roadmap&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitwarden Authenticator is a great and free addition to the existing TOTP-supporting applications and although it is still in its early stages, it already has the Bitwarden-flavour that I have loved since discovering it as my preferred password manager. For now, the codes it generates stand on their own without any connection to the password vault itself but with Phase 2 already coming with this feature, the physical separation of two important tools (password manager and 2FA app) based on one database could be yet another improvement for users’ security structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s still some work to be done, but even at this early stage, Bitwarden Authenticator is a great alternative to other apps and assuming you already trust Bitwarden with your password vault (or even host it yourself), why not use this app to refine your Bitwarden-powered security baseline?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/bitwarden-launches-new-mfa-authenticator-app/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/bitwarden-launches-new-mfa-authenticator-app/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>bitwarden</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                <category>security</category>
                
                <category>2fa</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Apple locks users out of their Apple IDs without explanation</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;security-and-big-tech-are-two-terms-that-dont-go-well-together-at-the-moment-after-ongoing-security-issues-at-microsoft-apple-seems-to-have-at-least-one-minor-problem-that-has-left-many-users-unexpectedly-locked-out-of-icloud-and-devices-belonging-to-it-and-forced-to-perform-an-unexpected-password-change-however-depending-on-apples-forthcoming-response-to-the-case-this-minor-problem-could-turn-into-a-serious-one&quot;&gt;“Security” and “big tech” are two terms that don’t go well together at the moment. After ongoing security issues at Microsoft, Apple seems to have at least one minor problem that has left many users unexpectedly locked out of iCloud and devices belonging to it and forced to perform an unexpected password change. However, depending on Apple’s forthcoming response to the case, this minor problem could turn into a serious one.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a simple day with your beloved Apple devices - to be honest, this is the status quo on pretty much every day. This Friday, I first noticed that my Apple Watch Ultra was unable to update the weather forecast and the current temperature. I had arrived at one of our offices early and was therefore not in a „trusted location“ - which are my home address and the nearest office, my main place of work. Suddenly I noticed that the Apple Watch was forcing me to verify the password of my Apple account (an old @mac.com one) out of nowhere. Then my iPhone came along with the same effect - feeling that something was very strange, I tried to access Apple’s [account page] (https://appleid.apple.com/) and discovered that my account was indeed locked, forcing me to recover it with a subsequent password change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/apple-id-down.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Apple ID down?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that I am a bit of a “tinfoil-hat” guy, as friends and colleagues call me, when it comes to security, I tried to find out what could be wrong. I haven’t added any new devices to my account, which is of course protected by 2FA, backed up by two YubiKey 5C NFC keys. iOS 17.3’s “Stolen Device Protection” is also enabled, and at the time of writing I was not using any applications that require an application password - which got deleted after the account reset by the way! The password I used for my beloved old @mac.com address is generated and definitely not something that could be guessed or brute-forced - the tinfoil-hat guy, remember?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I reset my password, knowing that I had some work to do at home later that evening. Two hours later, the same messages appeared again on my iPhone and Watch, so I went through the same process, feeling that something had to be wrong - and fearing that my account had some kind of security issue, especially since Apple’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/support/systemstatus/&quot;&gt;official status page&lt;/a&gt; didn’t show anything unusual. Anyway, with all the security options Apple provides, the likelihood of a security flaw should be quite low - but the issue concerned me anyway (and should concern anyone with a similar experience). So, maybe it was a technical issue or something that forced Apple to lock my account?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/apple_id.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Apple-devices&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, many people began reporting similar incidents around the world - many of them focusing on old @mac.com or @me.com addresses in the context of being the head of a family using the Family Sharing feature on iCloud.com. 9to5mac.com &lt;a href=&quot;https://9to5mac.com/2024/04/26/signed-out-of-apple-id-account-problem-password/&quot;&gt;reported the issue&lt;/a&gt; fairly early on and staff at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/daveywinder/2024/04/27/apple-id-password-reset-issue-hitting-iphone-ipad-and-macbook-users/&quot;&gt;Forbes&lt;/a&gt; had similar experiences. Also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2024/4/27/24142509/apple-id-logged-out-reset-stolen-device-protection&quot;&gt;The Verge got in line&lt;/a&gt; as well. The good news: I was not the only one. The bad: Nobody knew what was really going on because something was definitely wrong but Apple refused to comment on the issue, drawing the familiar veil of silence over the incident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, the Net has been flooded with news about the issue, so the whole thing seems to have a greater impact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://theinternet.social/@tbridge/112340463598872085&quot;&gt;Thread #1 on Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://eworld.social/@ismh/112340745553157794&quot;&gt;Thread #2 on Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mastodon.social/@ChrisLawley/112340853972099137&quot;&gt;Thread #3 on Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michael Tsai’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://mjtsai.com/blog/2024/04/26/janky-apple-id-security/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@singletary/post/C6P9jfJt1VH&quot;&gt;Threads #1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@andelirich/post/C6P88QiNY-J&quot;&gt;Threads #2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@adhdjesse/post/C6P9hS_L9_7&quot;&gt;Threads #3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@9six7/post/C6P-cP1sNu7&quot;&gt;Threads #4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@jubnub/post/C6P_DNyMVaT&quot;&gt;Threads #5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@timmeh71/post/C6P_b4prnWJ&quot;&gt;Threads #6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@ngorby/post/C6PvqnArUpZ&quot;&gt;Threads #7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@nichagan/post/C6Pzb8jLrvx&quot;&gt;More complaints on Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next-apple&quot;&gt;What’s next, Apple?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, among my friends and acquaintances, I was the only one affected - the only one with an “old” @mac.com-Apple ID. There was also no reaction in our family to similar effects (at least no one was texting or calling, so everything seems to be working). As The Net reports, Apple is downplaying the problem in terms of support calls and is not saying anything specific about “why” the whole thing happened in the first place. Personally, I could live with any explanation (precaution? attack? technical glitch?), as my security baseline is definitely more than just the simple standard, using all the options each vendor (in this case Apple) offers me but definitely there should be an official statement on this issue that has not just affected a few individual users. There is no need to diminish the relative importance of this case, and simply saying nothing is the wrong way to prove that “security” and “privacy” are still at the heart of Apple’s agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/igor-son-Nod1nQ0i5a0-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Apple-devices&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, we see that security is not a status quo, but an ongoing process. Vendor agnostic. It’s a process often paved with good intentions and a lot of backtracking, but it’s never finished. For every measure there is a countermeasure, and yes, I love Apple, my fenced (and falling down) garden and the products that grow in it (and are paid for by the users) but specifically in this frustrating and annoying case I want an answer - and I am not alone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So even as (or because being!) a loyal Apple fan and user for two decades, I have to ask the obvious question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you have to say about that, Apple?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/apple-locks-users-out-of-their-apple-ids-without-explanation/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/apple-locks-users-out-of-their-apple-ids-without-explanation/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>apple</category>
                
                <category>security</category>
                
                <category>2fa</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Microsoft adds recommended apps to the start menu in Windows 11</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;microsoft-is-currently-battling-a-lot-of-bad-press-but-as-if-that-wasnt-enough-theres-still-something-else-to-add-according-to-a-recent-blog-post-the-latest-windows-11-insider-preview-build-226353495-will-add-recommended-apps-to-the-users-start-menu---at-least-in-the-us-and-on-unmanaged-devices&quot;&gt;Microsoft is currently battling a lot of bad press but as if that wasn’t enough, there’s still something else to add: According to a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.windows.com/windows-insider/2024/04/12/announcing-windows-11-insider-preview-build-22635-3495-beta-channel/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;, the latest Windows 11 Insider Preview Build 22635.3495 will add recommended apps to the user’s start menu - at least in the US and on unmanaged devices.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this is only a test in a preview version of Windows 11, it is yet another ticked box on the list of foreign intrusion into the user’s operating system that is sadly part of Microsoft’s recent history. The unwanted &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2020/10/19/21524006/microsoft-pause-unsolicited-pwa-office-app-windows-10&quot;&gt;progressive web apps (PWAs) in Windows 10&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pifferi.info/new-outlook-seemingly-sends-sensitive-data-to-microsoft/&quot;&gt;privacy issue with the ‘new’ Outlook sending credentials to Redmond servers&lt;/a&gt; or this new issue raises the question of whether the installed operating system belongs to the user or is subject to Microsoft’s arbitrariness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/bekky-bekks-QRHRqOVOcfQ-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ads ahead!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, and whenever I have to deal with a client’s Windows system, I have never got used to the new “features” of grouping recently installed applications or showing frequently installed applications. This may have something to do with my own past when the classic Start menu had everything I needed. This was later superseded by these new features and in present days, whenever I have to deal with a Windows system, the combination of the Windows key and the ‘S’ is far quicker than any new idea from Redmond associated with the Start menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, as if that wasn’t enough already, the latest obvious idea is to recommend fancy and famous applications from the Microsoft Store in the Start menu even if you’ve never had a relationship with them. So, Redmond, what could possibly go wrong with this great new addition of useless bloatware to an operating system, cloaking this under the smoke screen of friendly recommendations to explore new, yet unknown apps?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/start-reco-1password.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A Microsoft genuine idea&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely this could just be another test balloon, with Redmond experimenting with new features that may (and hopefully) never make it to the final build. It’s also stated that only US-users enrolled in the Windows Insider program will be able to see this change and that it won’t apply to commercial devices (“devices managed by organizations”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have become accustomed to, these friendly recommendations can also be turned off by going to „Settings &amp;gt; Personalization &amp;gt; Start“ and unchecking the „Show recommendations for tips, app promotions and more“-box. Unfortunately they seem to be standard in this build and users will have to turn this feature off in the same way they can prevent the Start menu from showing frequently installed or used apps - once they made their way throughout the dazzling and confusing new system settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a reminder, we regularly try out new experiences and concepts that may never get released with Windows Insiders to get feedback. Should you see this experience on the Start menu, let us know what you think. We are beginning to roll this out to a small set of Insiders in the Beta Channel at first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-do-you-want-to-go-tomorrow-microsoft&quot;&gt;Where do you want to go tomorrow, Microsoft?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the phrase “it’s not a bug, it’s a feature”? It just popped into my head when I thought of those friendly additions to a simple operating system. Seemingly, Redmond lost its way on the desktop many years ago and while the focus is clearly on the cloud and the bundle of services that reside there, the desktop is somehow losing its historic role and adding pointless features to an end-user operating system may be one of the few facts that justify a new press release with leading the users to believe that there is an active development. There aren’t many features that justified ditching Windows 7 for Windows 10, and - in my humble opinion - there were even fewer that justified ditching Windows 10 in favour of Windows 11 and whatever may come. The desktop got boring and there aren’t that much justifications to slip creepy features to working operating systems without the user’s permission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the days of extraordinary changes on the desktop are over and operating systems are pretty mature - the same trend applies to my beloved macOS (at least for my use cases and personal needs). Instead of blowing these systems up, the focus should be on stripping them down to the bare essentials - with people being able to install the features they need, when they need them! The current trend coming out of Redmond is simply awful, and even if this is just a test in a preview version of Windows 11, the trend is clear - and the mistakes are being repeated over time. While the cloud is referred to as “just other people’s computers”, how do we ensure that using the latest iteration of Windows leaves us in control of our own PCs in the future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking of this, where do you want to go tomorrow, Microsoft?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/marcus-urbenz-hPA60HpZUrI-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A Microsoft genuine idea&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/microsoft-adds-recommended-apps-to-the-start-menu-in-windows-11/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/microsoft-adds-recommended-apps-to-the-start-menu-in-windows-11/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>microsoft</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                <category>windows</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>German state of Schleswig-Holstein bets on digital sovereignty for the modern workplace</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-open-source-strategy-in-german-states-and-municipalities-is-not-that-common-while-the-idea-of-decoupling-those-scopes-from-big-tech-isnt-that-new-just-remind-the-city-of-munichs-failed-linux-project-back-in-2017-reality-is-telling-yet-another-story-now-the-german-state-of-schleswig-holstein-has-recently-announced-a-new-workplace-strategy-based-on-digital-sovereignty&quot;&gt;An Open Source-strategy in German states and municipalities is not that common. While the idea of decoupling those scopes from Big Tech isn’t that new (just remind the city of Munich’s failed „Linux“-project back in 2017!), reality is telling yet another story. Now, the German state of Schleswig-Holstein has recently announced a new workplace strategy based on digital sovereignty.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just “Schleswig-Holstein against the trend”, it’s a statement that contains a lot of potential, but also the well-known sceptical thoughts about whether Linux and Open Source in general are able to replace Microsoft &amp;amp; Co. in public and governmental institutions. Call it “pioneering work”, but the realisation of this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schleswig-holstein.de/DE/landesregierung/ministerien-behoerden/I/_startseite/Artikel2024/II/240403_digitalsouveraene_verwaltung.html&quot;&gt;roadmap&lt;/a&gt; could indeed provide a real example that there can be a change in dependency if only every single sub-item on this long list of prerequisites can be marked as “checked”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-announcement&quot;&gt;The announcement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Einstieg in den Umstieg” is the slogan chosen by Schleswig-Holstein for the official announcement, meaning “entry into the change” - which says it all. While it’s not unusual for someone to try to switch from proprietary software to FOSS-based software, the fact that a German state has officially expressed this yearning for change is quite a groundbreaking proclamation, turning away from Big Tech-backed software (here) in the form of Microsoft-solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/schleswig_holstein.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hello, Schleswig-Holstein&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the banner of “independent, sustainable, secure”, Schleswig-Holstein wants to lead the way while being the first German state to introduce the modern workplace based on digital sovereignty in local government. Following a decision by the cabinet, the widespread adoption of LibreOffice as the standard office suite is just the first step and the starting point for a broader strategy aimed at complete digital sovereignty in the state of Schleswig-Holstein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;„The future of government is cloud-based, automated, algorithmic and data-driven. Therefore, all our future applications will be cloud-based. However, we don’t have any control over how data is processed, nor do we have any control over any data leakage.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Dirk Schrödter, Minister of Digitalization)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;„Our responsibility to the citizens of our state is to ensure that every single piece of data is kept secure and that we are always in control of the IT solutions we implement. Securing digital sovereignty is at least as important as securing power and energy sovereignty.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/christian-lue-8Yw6tsB8tnc-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Europe first&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;focusing-on-europe&quot;&gt;Focusing on Europe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dirk Schrödter also names the focus on Europe as one of the key factors for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schleswig-holstein.de/DE/landesregierung/ministerien-behoerden/I/Presse/PI/2024/CdS/240403_cds_it-arbeitsplatz.html?nn=549a8fa0-66c0-4da0-9f19-70e4be245eac&quot;&gt;new and pioneering digital strategy of Schleswig-Holstein&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;„The path to digital sovereignty follows a strict industrial policy compass: My vision of a strong digital garrison can only become a reality if we don’t have to invest our public budgets in licensing costs.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cabinet’s decision marks the start of the transition from proprietary software to free, Open Source-based solutions for some 30,000 users in the administration. Proprietary software refers to digital applications that are strictly limited in terms of copyright, licensing and further processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;„Instead, we can invest it in local digital companies and create local value and jobs. Our goals in developing a common digital single market are interconnected digital government solutions and services. As a government, we use the potential of data to create and secure innovation, value chains and wealth at home.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/dirk_schroeter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dirk Schrödter&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, these offerings are usually tied to data centre- or managed services which ultimately allows the product owner to retain sovereignty over these products and services - so breaking these dependencies is ultimately key to Schleswig-Holstein’s ongoing and future-based digital strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-factors&quot;&gt;The factors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s right, there are not seven pillars of wisdom, as T. E. Lawrence once wrote but only six, all of which are part of the digital sovereign workplace in the state of Schleswig-Holstein:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Replacement of Microsoft Office with LibreOffice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changing the basic OS from Microsoft Windows to Linux&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collaboration within the state administration and external parties: Using Open Source-solutions Nextcloud, Open Xchange/Thunderbird paired with Univention AD-Connector superseding Microsoft Sharepoint and Microsoft Exchange/Outlook&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A new approach with an Open Source-based directory service taking over from Microsoft Active Directory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inventory of the single specific procedures in terms of compatibility and interoperability with LibreOffice and Linux&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Development of an Open Source-related telephony solution replacing Telekom-Flexport&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All six together are said to provide a solid foundation for the digital challenges ahead. By switching to open source, Schleswig-Holstein is laying the foundations for creating, maintaining and preserving digital sovereignty. Pros such as increased IT security, efficiency, data protection and seamless cooperation between different software systems are cited as well as the goal of making future development results in the Open Source-sector available to the “greater whole” under the rights of free software licensing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to forget: Any change requires proper change management and with such a high turnover, user adoption is inevitable and a single beam carries the whole project: The use of LibreOffice for communication between departments and authorities is to be implemented in the short term, with exceptions in case the switch cannot be made for technical or professional reasons. According to Schleswig-Holstein there is already a wide range of training available for employees which will be expanded as needed. What’s more, the state’s central IT administration is making skilled staff available to ensure that user acceptance is not a showstopper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-two-cents&quot;&gt;My two cents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This step is a big signal. Despite the amount of work that still lies ahead for the IT administration of Schleswig-Holstein, this announcement and all its consequences could be THE initiator for the decoupling of old status quos that have always relied on Microsoft solutions. There is a use case for everything but considering the current dependencies and even pure facts in terms of security (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/microsoft-still-unsure-how-hackers-stole-msa-key-in-2023-exchange-attack/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cisa.gov/sites/default/files/2024-04/CSRB_Review_of_the_Summer_2023_MEO_Intrusion_Final_508c.pdf&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;), there should be an alternative to Big Tech - at least if the reappraisal of this whole bunch of unfortunate events within the attack chain is so sloppy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/shahadat-rahman-BfrQnKBulYQ-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Embracing Open Source&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this transition will take time - it certainly will - and the path of good intentions will be paved with delays, frustrations and other obstacles. On the other hand, the ultimate goal of creating digital sovereignty for an entire German state will be within reach, setting a good example for others to follow. Turning away from Microsoft-based solutions may be a sacrilege from many points of view, but there are alternatives to proprietary software - so if this project turns out to be a success (with the planned FOSS-based solutions, as advised), Schleswig-Holstein may iron out the manifestly bad experiences of Munich’s failed Linux migration which was ended back in 2017. Being independent of possible lobbying, turning to Open Source and contributing experience and code back to the community would be a shining example for other states (do you hear me, North Rhine-Westphalia?) to follow - or even whole governments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ball has been kicked into play and we may be eager to see the result - sometimes all it takes is an open mind, a courageous attitude and the ultimate will to keep going, even if the wind is blowing against you. The cold wind may turn into a vicious storm, but the visual signals are set to ‘Go’, so thumbs up and help from all quarters should be the least we can do to contribute to the cause!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/german-state-of-schleswig-holstein-bets-on-digital-sovereignty-for-the-modern-workplace/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/german-state-of-schleswig-holstein-bets-on-digital-sovereignty-for-the-modern-workplace/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>workplace</category>
                
                <category>opensource</category>
                
                <category>foss</category>
                
                <category>linux</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Was macht eine gute Backup-Strategie aus? Der World Backup Day 2024</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;am-heutigen-31-märz-ist-world-backup-day-wie-es-sich-gehört-und-mittlerweile-moderne-tradition-ist-benötigen-wir-einen-speziellen-tag-um-auf-ein-wichtiges-thema-nachhaltig-aufmerksam-zu-machen-der-world-backup-day-soll-erneut-an-die-bedeutung-von-datensicherungen--und-sicherheit-erinnern&quot;&gt;Am heutigen 31. März ist &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldbackupday.com/en&quot;&gt;World Backup Day&lt;/a&gt;. Wie es sich gehört und mittlerweile moderne Tradition ist, benötigen wir einen speziellen Tag, um auf ein wichtiges Thema nachhaltig aufmerksam zu machen. Der World Backup Day soll erneut an die Bedeutung von Datensicherungen- und Sicherheit erinnern.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In einem Zeitalter, wo das Sichern der eigenen Daten eine Selbstverständlichkeit darstellt und das Gefährdungspotential stetig ansteigt, muss das reine Backup nur ein Teil der gesamten Strategie sein. Doch was macht eine gute Backup-Strategie aus?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;die-historie&quot;&gt;Die Historie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der frühere Idealweg wurde durch die „3-2-1“-Regel definiert: Drei Backups auf zwei verschiedenen Medientypen und einer Kopie außer Haus - doch selbst das war und (leider auch) ist bei weitem nicht die Regel. Die Realität sieht oft anders aus - ein Backup auf ein Network Attached Storage im selben Raum mag prinzipiell ein Backup sein, eine Strategie steht dahinter aber eher weniger. Diese Denkweise findet man teilweise noch in kleineren Unternehmen, wo ein Backup samt verläßlicher (und ergo oft kostenpflichtiger) Software eher ein „notwendiges Übel“ darstellt. Recovery Tests werden mäßig bis gar nicht durchgeführt, ein Monitoring des Backups geschieht per se sowieso nicht und nach einem dedizierten Sicherung-Konzept braucht man dann eher auch nicht fragen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/chris-yates-iqELIpzpARI-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s World Backup Day - again&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In dem Moment, wo ein zeitlicher Ausfall (aus welchen Gründen auch immer) geschieht, die Uhr klar gegen das Unternehmen tickt und die Faktoren RTO und RPO unbarmherzig in den Fokus rücken, wird schnell klar, dass auch beim Backup eine Strategie unerläßlich und - ja! - lebenswichtig ist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;der-zeit-faktor&quot;&gt;Der Zeit-Faktor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zur Erklärung: Das Recovery Point Objective (RPO) bezieht sich im Allgemeinen auf die Berechnung der Menge an Datenverlusten, die ein Unternehmen innerhalb eines für sein Geschäft relevanten Zeitraums erleiden kann, bevor ein signifikanter Schaden entsteht - und zwar vom Zeitpunkt eines Störungsereignisses bis zur letzten Datensicherung. Redet man also über eine Strategie, so muss man auch zwangsläufig über diesen Faktor reden, der durchaus die erste Risikoklassifizierung darstellt. Die Wiederherstellungszeit (Recovery Time Objective, RTO) wiederum bezieht sich generell auf die Zeit, die eine Anwendung, ein System oder ein Prozess ausfallen kann, ohne dass ein erheblicher Schaden für das Unternehmen entsteht.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/nathan-dumlao-LPRrEJU2GbQ-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s World Backup Day - again&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ebenso steht sie in Verbindung mit der Zeit, die für die Wiederherstellung der Anwendung und ihrer Daten benötigt wird, um den normalen Geschäftsbetrieb nach einem schwerwiegenden Vorfall wieder aufzunehmen: Aus Erfahrung tickt im Worst Case die Uhr gnadenlos gegen die Betroffenen und das eine Backup mag die Daten enthalten, die Rücksicherung dauert aber quälend lange. Sofern also etwas passiert ist, sollte man sich nicht erst dann Gedanken über den Faktor „Zeit“ machen müssen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;die-strategie&quot;&gt;Die Strategie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hat man bereits über RTO und RPO gesprochen, so spricht man unweigerlich auch über das Backup-Konzept, die Mittel (Hard- wie Software) und am Ende eben über die gesamte Strategie: Ein Backup-Server gehört nicht in eine Active Directory-Domäne und er sollte idealerweise auch keinen virtueller Server auf der eigentlich zu sichernden Umgebung darstellen. Idealerweise ist er auch physisch getrennt von den Produktivsystem - ebenso wie die weiteren Repositories, die die Backups enthalten, beispielsweise in einem anderen, unabdingbaren Brandabschnitt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/mark-fletcher-brown-nN5L5GXKFz8-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s World Backup Day - again&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auch die 3-2-1-Regel ist längst nicht mehr der Weisheit letzter Schluß, wie es bereits Veeam seit einiger Zeit beschreibt. Sie wird durch die 3-2-1-1-0-Regel abgelöst, die der Hersteller auch als „goldene Regel“ tituliert: Vorhalten dreier Kopien-/Backups der Daten, Sicherung dieser Backups auf zwei verschiedene Medientypen, Erstellung mindestens einer Offsite- sowie einer Offline-Kopie (Stichwort „Medientrennung“) und die finale „0“ in Form der Verifizierung der getätigten Backups ohne jeglichen Fehler: Das klingt komplex, ist es aber nicht, wenn man seinen Daten entsprechende Priorität einräumt, die Pflichten, Rechte wie auch Risiken in Bezug auf Backups klassifiziert und die richtigen Partner und Dienste an seiner Seite weiß.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ein-vorläufiges-fazit&quot;&gt;Ein (vorläufiges) Fazit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein Produkt macht noch keine Lösung. Ein Backup noch keine Strategie. Sicherungs-Software, die mit dem „Weiter-Weiter-Fertig“-Installationsweg deployed wird, ist trotz eines möglichen ersten vollständigen Backups weit entfernt von einem wasserdichten Konzept. Das Tape ist (gerade in großen Umgebungen) immer noch nicht tot: Fragen Sie einmal &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibm.com/tape-storage&quot;&gt;IBM&lt;/a&gt;! Ein Restore sollte nur erfolgen, wenn das Backup Ransomware-frei ist: &lt;a href=&quot;https://community.veeam.com/blogs-and-podcasts-57/ransomware-proof-backups-configuring-and-integrating-object-first-with-veeam-vbr-6930&quot;&gt;Veeam&lt;/a&gt; zeigt, wie das funktionieren kann! Ein (selbstverständlich selbst) verschlüsseltes Backup auszulagern, kann mit Bordmitteln auch zu einem vertrauenswürdigen Cloud Service Provider, beispielsweise in die &lt;a href=&quot;https://enthus.de/services-xaas/xaas/enthus-cloud&quot;&gt;enthus Cloud&lt;/a&gt;, erfolgen - und wer am Ende auch noch ein Disaster Recovery-Ansatz erfolgt, wird hier ebenfalls fündig: Zusammen mit der &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hpe.com/de/de/storage/data-protection-solutions/disaster-recovery-zerto.html&quot;&gt;Zerto&lt;/a&gt; von &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hpe.com/de/de/storage/data-protection-solutions/disaster-recovery-zerto.html&quot;&gt;HPE&lt;/a&gt; lassen sich Backups und DRaaS wunderbar gemeinsam betreiben und die Ausfallsicherheit je nach Anforderungen nahezu gen Null fahren!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/wbd_horizontal-date.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s World Backup Day - again&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Das sind nur einige Möglichkeiten, derer man im Rahmen dieses jährlich wiederkehrenden World Backups Day „gedenkt“. Eine allgemeine, für jeden Anwendungsfall geltende, Backup-Strategie gibt es nicht. Primär muss verstanden werden, dass vieles, was wir heute als „Backup“ definieren, kein wirkliches ist respektive von einer Backup-Strategie weit entfernt ist. Am Ende kommt es auf das geschärfte Bewusstsein in einer voller Bedrohungslagen gespickten Zeit, die passenden Werkzeuge und Partner an - und auf ein Konzept, dass individuell für den eigenen Use Case zugeschnitten ist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dieses Konzept sollte nicht starr sein, sondern dynamisch an die Möglichkeiten des Marktes und vor allem den eigenen, wechselnden Anforderungen angepasst werden - denn so, wie sich Softwarekomponenten, Partnerlandschaften und Hardware ändern, ändern sich auch die eigenen Anforderungen häufiger, als man es glauben mag. All das zusammen zählt auf eine gute Backup-Strategie ein und hilft auch, künftigen Herausforderungen gelassener entgegenzutreten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In diesem Sinne einen happy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldbackupday.com/en&quot;&gt;World Backup Day 2024&lt;/a&gt; und frohe Ostern!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/was-macht-eine-gute-backup-strategie-aus-der-world-backup-day-2024/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/was-macht-eine-gute-backup-strategie-aus-der-world-backup-day-2024/</guid>
                
                <category>backup</category>
                
                <category>strategy</category>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>security</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>