<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Oliver&apos;s Blog</title>
        <description>My own small private space in the world of bewitched madness!</description>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
        <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 21:54:34 +0200</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 21:54:34 +0200</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.3.3</generator>
        
            <item>
                <title>Microsoft adds recommended apps to the start menu in Windows 11</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;microsoft-is-currently-battling-a-lot-of-bad-press-but-as-if-that-wasnt-enough-theres-still-something-else-to-add-according-to-a-recent-blog-post-the-latest-windows-11-insider-preview-build-226353495-will-add-recommended-apps-to-the-users-start-menu---at-least-in-the-us-and-on-unmanaged-devices&quot;&gt;Microsoft is currently battling a lot of bad press but as if that wasn’t enough, there’s still something else to add: According to a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.windows.com/windows-insider/2024/04/12/announcing-windows-11-insider-preview-build-22635-3495-beta-channel/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;, the latest Windows 11 Insider Preview Build 22635.3495 will add recommended apps to the user’s start menu - at least in the US and on unmanaged devices.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this is only a test in a preview version of Windows 11, it is yet another ticked box on the list of foreign intrusion into the user’s operating system that is sadly part of Microsoft’s recent history. The unwanted &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2020/10/19/21524006/microsoft-pause-unsolicited-pwa-office-app-windows-10&quot;&gt;progressive web apps (PWAs) in Windows 10&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pifferi.info/new-outlook-seemingly-sends-sensitive-data-to-microsoft/&quot;&gt;privacy issue with the ‘new’ Outlook sending credentials to Redmond servers&lt;/a&gt; or this new issue raises the question of whether the installed operating system belongs to the user or is subject to Microsoft’s arbitrariness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/bekky-bekks-QRHRqOVOcfQ-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ads ahead!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, and whenever I have to deal with a client’s Windows system, I have never got used to the new “features” of grouping recently installed applications or showing frequently installed applications. This may have something to do with my own past when the classic Start menu had everything I needed. This was later superseded by these new features and in present days, whenever I have to deal with a Windows system, the combination of the Windows key and the ‘S’ is far quicker than any new idea from Redmond associated with the Start menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, as if that wasn’t enough already, the latest obvious idea is to recommend fancy and famous applications from the Microsoft Store in the Start menu even if you’ve never had a relationship with them. So, Redmond, what could possibly go wrong with this great new addition of useless bloatware to an operating system, cloaking this under the smoke screen of friendly recommendations to explore new, yet unknown apps?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/start-reco-1password.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A Microsoft genuine idea&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely this could just be another test balloon, with Redmond experimenting with new features that may (and hopefully) never make it to the final build. It’s also stated that only US-users enrolled in the Windows Insider program will be able to see this change and that it won’t apply to commercial devices (“devices managed by organizations”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have become accustomed to, these friendly recommendations can also be turned off by going to „Settings &amp;gt; Personalization &amp;gt; Start“ and unchecking the „Show recommendations for tips, app promotions and more“-box. Unfortunately they seem to be standard in this build and users will have to turn this feature off in the same way they can prevent the Start menu from showing frequently installed or used apps - once they made their way throughout the dazzling and confusing new system settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a reminder, we regularly try out new experiences and concepts that may never get released with Windows Insiders to get feedback. Should you see this experience on the Start menu, let us know what you think. We are beginning to roll this out to a small set of Insiders in the Beta Channel at first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-do-you-want-to-go-tomorrow-microsoft&quot;&gt;Where do you want to go tomorrow, Microsoft?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the phrase “it’s not a bug, it’s a feature”? It just popped into my head when I thought of those friendly additions to a simple operating system. Seemingly, Redmond lost its way on the desktop many years ago and while the focus is clearly on the cloud and the bundle of services that reside there, the desktop is somehow losing its historic role and adding pointless features to an end-user operating system may be one of the few facts that justify a new press release with leading the users to believe that there is an active development. There aren’t many features that justified ditching Windows 7 for Windows 10, and - in my humble opinion - there were even fewer that justified ditching Windows 10 in favour of Windows 11 and whatever may come. The desktop got boring and there aren’t that much justifications to slip creepy features to working operating systems without the user’s permission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the days of extraordinary changes on the desktop are over and operating systems are pretty mature - the same trend applies to my beloved macOS (at least for my use cases and personal needs). Instead of blowing these systems up, the focus should be on stripping them down to the bare essentials - with people being able to install the features they need, when they need them! The current trend coming out of Redmond is simply awful, and even if this is just a test in a preview version of Windows 11, the trend is clear - and the mistakes are being repeated over time. While the cloud is referred to as “just other people’s computers”, how do we ensure that using the latest iteration of Windows leaves us in control of our own PCs in the future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking of this, where do you want to go tomorrow, Microsoft?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/marcus-urbenz-hPA60HpZUrI-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A Microsoft genuine idea&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/microsoft-adds-recommended-apps-to-the-start-menu-in-windows-11/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/microsoft-adds-recommended-apps-to-the-start-menu-in-windows-11/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>microsoft</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                <category>windows</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>German state of Schleswig-Holstein bets on digital sovereignty for the modern workplace</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-open-source-strategy-in-german-states-and-municipalities-is-not-that-common-while-the-idea-of-decoupling-those-scopes-from-big-tech-isnt-that-new-just-remind-the-city-of-munichs-failed-linux-project-back-in-2017-reality-is-telling-yet-another-story-now-the-german-state-of-schleswig-holstein-has-recently-announced-a-new-workplace-strategy-based-on-digital-sovereignty&quot;&gt;An Open Source-strategy in German states and municipalities is not that common. While the idea of decoupling those scopes from Big Tech isn’t that new (just remind the city of Munich’s failed „Linux“-project back in 2017!), reality is telling yet another story. Now, the German state of Schleswig-Holstein has recently announced a new workplace strategy based on digital sovereignty.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just “Schleswig-Holstein against the trend”, it’s a statement that contains a lot of potential, but also the well-known sceptical thoughts about whether Linux and Open Source in general are able to replace Microsoft &amp;amp; Co. in public and governmental institutions. Call it “pioneering work”, but the realisation of this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schleswig-holstein.de/DE/landesregierung/ministerien-behoerden/I/_startseite/Artikel2024/II/240403_digitalsouveraene_verwaltung.html&quot;&gt;roadmap&lt;/a&gt; could indeed provide a real example that there can be a change in dependency if only every single sub-item on this long list of prerequisites can be marked as “checked”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-announcement&quot;&gt;The announcement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Einstieg in den Umstieg” is the slogan chosen by Schleswig-Holstein for the official announcement, meaning “entry into the change” - which says it all. While it’s not unusual for someone to try to switch from proprietary software to FOSS-based software, the fact that a German state has officially expressed this yearning for change is quite a groundbreaking proclamation, turning away from Big Tech-backed software (here) in the form of Microsoft-solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/schleswig_holstein.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hello, Schleswig-Holstein&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the banner of “independent, sustainable, secure”, Schleswig-Holstein wants to lead the way while being the first German state to introduce the modern workplace based on digital sovereignty in local government. Following a decision by the cabinet, the widespread adoption of LibreOffice as the standard office suite is just the first step and the starting point for a broader strategy aimed at complete digital sovereignty in the state of Schleswig-Holstein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;„The future of government is cloud-based, automated, algorithmic and data-driven. Therefore, all our future applications will be cloud-based. However, we don’t have any control over how data is processed, nor do we have any control over any data leakage.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Dirk Schrödter, Minister of Digitalization)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;„Our responsibility to the citizens of our state is to ensure that every single piece of data is kept secure and that we are always in control of the IT solutions we implement. Securing digital sovereignty is at least as important as securing power and energy sovereignty.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/christian-lue-8Yw6tsB8tnc-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Europe first&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;focusing-on-europe&quot;&gt;Focusing on Europe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dirk Schrödter also names the focus on Europe as one of the key factors for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schleswig-holstein.de/DE/landesregierung/ministerien-behoerden/I/Presse/PI/2024/CdS/240403_cds_it-arbeitsplatz.html?nn=549a8fa0-66c0-4da0-9f19-70e4be245eac&quot;&gt;new and pioneering digital strategy of Schleswig-Holstein&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;„The path to digital sovereignty follows a strict industrial policy compass: My vision of a strong digital garrison can only become a reality if we don’t have to invest our public budgets in licensing costs.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cabinet’s decision marks the start of the transition from proprietary software to free, Open Source-based solutions for some 30,000 users in the administration. Proprietary software refers to digital applications that are strictly limited in terms of copyright, licensing and further processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;„Instead, we can invest it in local digital companies and create local value and jobs. Our goals in developing a common digital single market are interconnected digital government solutions and services. As a government, we use the potential of data to create and secure innovation, value chains and wealth at home.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/dirk_schroeter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dirk Schrödter&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, these offerings are usually tied to data centre- or managed services which ultimately allows the product owner to retain sovereignty over these products and services - so breaking these dependencies is ultimately key to Schleswig-Holstein’s ongoing and future-based digital strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-factors&quot;&gt;The factors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s right, there are not seven pillars of wisdom, as T. E. Lawrence once wrote but only six, all of which are part of the digital sovereign workplace in the state of Schleswig-Holstein:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Replacement of Microsoft Office with LibreOffice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changing the basic OS from Microsoft Windows to Linux&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collaboration within the state administration and external parties: Using Open Source-solutions Nextcloud, Open Xchange/Thunderbird paired with Univention AD-Connector superseding Microsoft Sharepoint and Microsoft Exchange/Outlook&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A new approach with an Open Source-based directory service taking over from Microsoft Active Directory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inventory of the single specific procedures in terms of compatibility and interoperability with LibreOffice and Linux&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Development of an Open Source-related telephony solution replacing Telekom-Flexport&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All six together are said to provide a solid foundation for the digital challenges ahead. By switching to open source, Schleswig-Holstein is laying the foundations for creating, maintaining and preserving digital sovereignty. Pros such as increased IT security, efficiency, data protection and seamless cooperation between different software systems are cited as well as the goal of making future development results in the Open Source-sector available to the “greater whole” under the rights of free software licensing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to forget: Any change requires proper change management and with such a high turnover, user adoption is inevitable and a single beam carries the whole project: The use of LibreOffice for communication between departments and authorities is to be implemented in the short term, with exceptions in case the switch cannot be made for technical or professional reasons. According to Schleswig-Holstein there is already a wide range of training available for employees which will be expanded as needed. What’s more, the state’s central IT administration is making skilled staff available to ensure that user acceptance is not a showstopper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-two-cents&quot;&gt;My two cents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This step is a big signal. Despite the amount of work that still lies ahead for the IT administration of Schleswig-Holstein, this announcement and all its consequences could be THE initiator for the decoupling of old status quos that have always relied on Microsoft solutions. There is a use case for everything but considering the current dependencies and even pure facts in terms of security (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/microsoft-still-unsure-how-hackers-stole-msa-key-in-2023-exchange-attack/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cisa.gov/sites/default/files/2024-04/CSRB_Review_of_the_Summer_2023_MEO_Intrusion_Final_508c.pdf&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;), there should be an alternative to Big Tech - at least if the reappraisal of this whole bunch of unfortunate events within the attack chain is so sloppy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/shahadat-rahman-BfrQnKBulYQ-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Embracing Open Source&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this transition will take time - it certainly will - and the path of good intentions will be paved with delays, frustrations and other obstacles. On the other hand, the ultimate goal of creating digital sovereignty for an entire German state will be within reach, setting a good example for others to follow. Turning away from Microsoft-based solutions may be a sacrilege from many points of view, but there are alternatives to proprietary software - so if this project turns out to be a success (with the planned FOSS-based solutions, as advised), Schleswig-Holstein may iron out the manifestly bad experiences of Munich’s failed Linux migration which was ended back in 2017. Being independent of possible lobbying, turning to Open Source and contributing experience and code back to the community would be a shining example for other states (do you hear me, North Rhine-Westphalia?) to follow - or even whole governments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ball has been kicked into play and we may be eager to see the result - sometimes all it takes is an open mind, a courageous attitude and the ultimate will to keep going, even if the wind is blowing against you. The cold wind may turn into a vicious storm, but the visual signals are set to ‘Go’, so thumbs up and help from all quarters should be the least we can do to contribute to the cause!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/german-state-of-schleswig-holstein-bets-on-digital-sovereignty-for-the-modern-workplace/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/german-state-of-schleswig-holstein-bets-on-digital-sovereignty-for-the-modern-workplace/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>workplace</category>
                
                <category>opensource</category>
                
                <category>foss</category>
                
                <category>linux</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Was macht eine gute Backup-Strategie aus? Der World Backup Day 2024</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;am-heutigen-31-märz-ist-world-backup-day-wie-es-sich-gehört-und-mittlerweile-moderne-tradition-ist-benötigen-wir-einen-speziellen-tag-um-auf-ein-wichtiges-thema-nachhaltig-aufmerksam-zu-machen-der-world-backup-day-soll-erneut-an-die-bedeutung-von-datensicherungen--und-sicherheit-erinnern&quot;&gt;Am heutigen 31. März ist &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldbackupday.com/en&quot;&gt;World Backup Day&lt;/a&gt;. Wie es sich gehört und mittlerweile moderne Tradition ist, benötigen wir einen speziellen Tag, um auf ein wichtiges Thema nachhaltig aufmerksam zu machen. Der World Backup Day soll erneut an die Bedeutung von Datensicherungen- und Sicherheit erinnern.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In einem Zeitalter, wo das Sichern der eigenen Daten eine Selbstverständlichkeit darstellt und das Gefährdungspotential stetig ansteigt, muss das reine Backup nur ein Teil der gesamten Strategie sein. Doch was macht eine gute Backup-Strategie aus?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;die-historie&quot;&gt;Die Historie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der frühere Idealweg wurde durch die „3-2-1“-Regel definiert: Drei Backups auf zwei verschiedenen Medientypen und einer Kopie außer Haus - doch selbst das war und (leider auch) ist bei weitem nicht die Regel. Die Realität sieht oft anders aus - ein Backup auf ein Network Attached Storage im selben Raum mag prinzipiell ein Backup sein, eine Strategie steht dahinter aber eher weniger. Diese Denkweise findet man teilweise noch in kleineren Unternehmen, wo ein Backup samt verläßlicher (und ergo oft kostenpflichtiger) Software eher ein „notwendiges Übel“ darstellt. Recovery Tests werden mäßig bis gar nicht durchgeführt, ein Monitoring des Backups geschieht per se sowieso nicht und nach einem dedizierten Sicherung-Konzept braucht man dann eher auch nicht fragen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/chris-yates-iqELIpzpARI-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s World Backup Day - again&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In dem Moment, wo ein zeitlicher Ausfall (aus welchen Gründen auch immer) geschieht, die Uhr klar gegen das Unternehmen tickt und die Faktoren RTO und RPO unbarmherzig in den Fokus rücken, wird schnell klar, dass auch beim Backup eine Strategie unerläßlich und - ja! - lebenswichtig ist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;der-zeit-faktor&quot;&gt;Der Zeit-Faktor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zur Erklärung: Das Recovery Point Objective (RPO) bezieht sich im Allgemeinen auf die Berechnung der Menge an Datenverlusten, die ein Unternehmen innerhalb eines für sein Geschäft relevanten Zeitraums erleiden kann, bevor ein signifikanter Schaden entsteht - und zwar vom Zeitpunkt eines Störungsereignisses bis zur letzten Datensicherung. Redet man also über eine Strategie, so muss man auch zwangsläufig über diesen Faktor reden, der durchaus die erste Risikoklassifizierung darstellt. Die Wiederherstellungszeit (Recovery Time Objective, RTO) wiederum bezieht sich generell auf die Zeit, die eine Anwendung, ein System oder ein Prozess ausfallen kann, ohne dass ein erheblicher Schaden für das Unternehmen entsteht.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/nathan-dumlao-LPRrEJU2GbQ-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s World Backup Day - again&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ebenso steht sie in Verbindung mit der Zeit, die für die Wiederherstellung der Anwendung und ihrer Daten benötigt wird, um den normalen Geschäftsbetrieb nach einem schwerwiegenden Vorfall wieder aufzunehmen: Aus Erfahrung tickt im Worst Case die Uhr gnadenlos gegen die Betroffenen und das eine Backup mag die Daten enthalten, die Rücksicherung dauert aber quälend lange. Sofern also etwas passiert ist, sollte man sich nicht erst dann Gedanken über den Faktor „Zeit“ machen müssen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;die-strategie&quot;&gt;Die Strategie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hat man bereits über RTO und RPO gesprochen, so spricht man unweigerlich auch über das Backup-Konzept, die Mittel (Hard- wie Software) und am Ende eben über die gesamte Strategie: Ein Backup-Server gehört nicht in eine Active Directory-Domäne und er sollte idealerweise auch keinen virtueller Server auf der eigentlich zu sichernden Umgebung darstellen. Idealerweise ist er auch physisch getrennt von den Produktivsystem - ebenso wie die weiteren Repositories, die die Backups enthalten, beispielsweise in einem anderen, unabdingbaren Brandabschnitt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/mark-fletcher-brown-nN5L5GXKFz8-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s World Backup Day - again&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auch die 3-2-1-Regel ist längst nicht mehr der Weisheit letzter Schluß, wie es bereits Veeam seit einiger Zeit beschreibt. Sie wird durch die 3-2-1-1-0-Regel abgelöst, die der Hersteller auch als „goldene Regel“ tituliert: Vorhalten dreier Kopien-/Backups der Daten, Sicherung dieser Backups auf zwei verschiedene Medientypen, Erstellung mindestens einer Offsite- sowie einer Offline-Kopie (Stichwort „Medientrennung“) und die finale „0“ in Form der Verifizierung der getätigten Backups ohne jeglichen Fehler: Das klingt komplex, ist es aber nicht, wenn man seinen Daten entsprechende Priorität einräumt, die Pflichten, Rechte wie auch Risiken in Bezug auf Backups klassifiziert und die richtigen Partner und Dienste an seiner Seite weiß.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ein-vorläufiges-fazit&quot;&gt;Ein (vorläufiges) Fazit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein Produkt macht noch keine Lösung. Ein Backup noch keine Strategie. Sicherungs-Software, die mit dem „Weiter-Weiter-Fertig“-Installationsweg deployed wird, ist trotz eines möglichen ersten vollständigen Backups weit entfernt von einem wasserdichten Konzept. Das Tape ist (gerade in großen Umgebungen) immer noch nicht tot: Fragen Sie einmal &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibm.com/tape-storage&quot;&gt;IBM&lt;/a&gt;! Ein Restore sollte nur erfolgen, wenn das Backup Ransomware-frei ist: &lt;a href=&quot;https://community.veeam.com/blogs-and-podcasts-57/ransomware-proof-backups-configuring-and-integrating-object-first-with-veeam-vbr-6930&quot;&gt;Veeam&lt;/a&gt; zeigt, wie das funktionieren kann! Ein (selbstverständlich selbst) verschlüsseltes Backup auszulagern, kann mit Bordmitteln auch zu einem vertrauenswürdigen Cloud Service Provider, beispielsweise in die &lt;a href=&quot;https://enthus.de/services-xaas/xaas/enthus-cloud&quot;&gt;enthus Cloud&lt;/a&gt;, erfolgen - und wer am Ende auch noch ein Disaster Recovery-Ansatz erfolgt, wird hier ebenfalls fündig: Zusammen mit der &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hpe.com/de/de/storage/data-protection-solutions/disaster-recovery-zerto.html&quot;&gt;Zerto&lt;/a&gt; von &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hpe.com/de/de/storage/data-protection-solutions/disaster-recovery-zerto.html&quot;&gt;HPE&lt;/a&gt; lassen sich Backups und DRaaS wunderbar gemeinsam betreiben und die Ausfallsicherheit je nach Anforderungen nahezu gen Null fahren!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/wbd_horizontal-date.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s World Backup Day - again&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Das sind nur einige Möglichkeiten, derer man im Rahmen dieses jährlich wiederkehrenden World Backups Day „gedenkt“. Eine allgemeine, für jeden Anwendungsfall geltende, Backup-Strategie gibt es nicht. Primär muss verstanden werden, dass vieles, was wir heute als „Backup“ definieren, kein wirkliches ist respektive von einer Backup-Strategie weit entfernt ist. Am Ende kommt es auf das geschärfte Bewusstsein in einer voller Bedrohungslagen gespickten Zeit, die passenden Werkzeuge und Partner an - und auf ein Konzept, dass individuell für den eigenen Use Case zugeschnitten ist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dieses Konzept sollte nicht starr sein, sondern dynamisch an die Möglichkeiten des Marktes und vor allem den eigenen, wechselnden Anforderungen angepasst werden - denn so, wie sich Softwarekomponenten, Partnerlandschaften und Hardware ändern, ändern sich auch die eigenen Anforderungen häufiger, als man es glauben mag. All das zusammen zählt auf eine gute Backup-Strategie ein und hilft auch, künftigen Herausforderungen gelassener entgegenzutreten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In diesem Sinne einen happy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldbackupday.com/en&quot;&gt;World Backup Day 2024&lt;/a&gt; und frohe Ostern!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/was-macht-eine-gute-backup-strategie-aus-der-world-backup-day-2024/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/was-macht-eine-gute-backup-strategie-aus-der-world-backup-day-2024/</guid>
                
                <category>backup</category>
                
                <category>strategy</category>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>security</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Microsoft Edge bug could have enabled attackers to install malicious extensions without detection</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;years-ago-i-took-my-first-steps-on-the-internet-with-netscape-navigator-today-browsers-serve-more-than-just-as-a-gateway-to-the-world-wide-web-they-are-essential-software-for-many-purposes-in-our-digital-world-but-also-a-surface-for-modern-attacks&quot;&gt;Years ago, I took my first steps on the internet with Netscape Navigator. Today, browsers serve more than just as a gateway to the World Wide Web. They are essential software for many purposes in our digital world but also a surface for modern attacks.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I prefer to use Safari and Firefox for personal browsing and keep my browsers free of excessive extensions, the situation is different in my business setting. Due to its seamless integration with Microsoft 365 and its underlying services, Edge is the preferred browser here. Although the Chromium-based browser was initially a promising alternative to Google’s Chrome in 2019, it has since become burdened with unnecessary integrations and privacy concerns, both for private users and businesses. Unfortunately, Edge has become quite similar to Google Chrome over time but with a Redmond flavor and a recently reported, serious security issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/microsoft_edge_attack_chain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Attack chain&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-has-happened&quot;&gt;What has happened?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehackernews.com&quot;&gt;The Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; has recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehackernews.com/2024/03/microsoft-edge-bug-could-have-allowed.html&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt;, a now-patched security flaw in the browser’s engine could have been abused to install arbitrary extensions on users’ systems and carry out malicious actions in the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This flaw could have allowed an attacker to exploit a private API, initially intended for marketing purposes, to covertly install additional browser extensions with broad permissions without the user’s knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Oleg Zaytsev, security researcher from Guardio Labs)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zaytsev reported an issue with „&lt;a href=&quot;https://labs.guard.io/cve-2024-21388-microsoft-edges-marketing-api-exploited-for-covert-extension-installation-879fe5ad35ca&quot;&gt;Microsoft Edge’s Marketing API being exploited for covert extension installation&lt;/a&gt;“ which was tracked as &lt;a href=&quot;https://msrc.microsoft.com/update-guide/vulnerability/CVE-2024-21388&quot;&gt;CVE-2024-21388&lt;/a&gt; with a CVSS score of 6.5. Microsoft addressed the issue in Edge’s stable versions 121.0.2277.83 released on January 25, 2024, following responsible disclosure in November 2023. Both Zaytsev and Jun Kokatsu were credited by Redmond for reporting this severe exploit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An attacker who successfully exploited this vulnerability could gain the privileges needed to install an extension&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft said in an advisory for the flaw, also adding it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;could lead to a browser sandbox escape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technical-details-of-the-case&quot;&gt;Technical details of the case&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically naming it a privilege escalation flaw, Redmond also emphasizes that a successful exploitation of the bug requires an attacker to “take additional actions prior to exploitation to prepare the target environment.” Thus spoken, this is no „exploit in the wild“ but a not-that-unimportant surface attack nevertheless. According to Guardio’s research, &lt;a href=&quot;https://msrc.microsoft.com/update-guide/vulnerability/CVE-2024-21388&quot;&gt;CVE-2024-21388&lt;/a&gt; also enables a malicious actor to install any extensions from the Edge Add-On store without requiring the user’s explicit consent or interaction. This can be done by running JavaScript on bing.com (well…) or on any of the numerous microsoft.com-pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/microsoft_edge_type_of_validation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Type of validation in MS Edge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically, the browser can install an add-on from the vendor’s own extension marketplace because it has privileged access to certain private APIs. One such APIs in the Chromium-based Edge browser is „edgeMarketingPagePrivate“ which is accessible from a set of allowlisted websites that belong to Microsoft, including bing.com, microsoft.com, microsoftedgewelcome.microsoft.com and microsoftedgetips.microsoft.com - just to name a few!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The API also packs in a method called installTheme() that, as the name implies, is designed to install a theme from the Edge Add-ons store by passing a unique theme identifier (“themeId”) and its manifest file as input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As an added bonus, as this extension installation is not done quite in the manner it was originally designed for, there will be no need for any interaction or consent from the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, an attacker could use CVE-2024-21388 to publish a seemingly harmless extension to the add-ons store and inject malicious JavaScript code into bing.com or other allowed sites. This would allow them to install an arbitrary extension of their choice by invoking the API using the extension identifier. In other words: If the specially crafted extension is executed on the Edge-browser and the user visits, for example, bing.com, the targeted extension will be installed without their consent and the malicious payload can be deployed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/microsoft_edge_extension_installation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Extension installation in MS Edge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guardio Labs reported that although there is no evidence of this bug being exploited in the wild, it highlights the need to balance user convenience and security. Browser customizations can inadvertently defeat security mechanisms and introduce several new attack vectors in areas a simple browsing user would never expect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s relatively easy for attackers to trick users into installing an extension that appears harmless, not realizing it serves as the initial step in a more complex attack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zaytsev said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This vulnerability could be exploited to facilitate the installation of additional extensions, potentially for monetary gain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-opinion&quot;&gt;Final opinion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, and in my personal opinion, Edge has become the same monolith that Chrome already is. When it first appeared in 2019 and rose from the ashes of the inglorious first Edge browser, I was more than happy that there was a modern, supported and actively maintained browser with the Chromium engine without the Google bloatware and bad stuff lurking under the surface. Edge’s evolution over the past two years has already seen the changing times, and with many useless features, new (and even more useless) sidebars, and lots of Redmond reporting stuff under the hood, it is more than obvious that Microsoft has lost the essence of being an alternative to Google Chrome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no security by design, and security is not a status quo, but an ongoing process. This also applies to modern browsers, but with more and more features added to a simple browser (with tracking capabilities and framing in the M365 microcosm), Edge has reached the same level as Google Chrome - it just depends on the users whether they are connected to the Google or Microsoft world. Of course, there are many alternatives (did anyone say „&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ungoogled-software/ungoogled-chromium&quot;&gt;ungoogled-chromium&lt;/a&gt;“?), but considering the evolution of browsers over the years, there are not many positive aspects left if you just want to browse the web without built-in trackers, crypto stuff or other fancy crap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There should be a feature freeze (or reduction) coupled with a rethinking of what a browser should basically do for home users, businesses, and people who just don’t want their data exposed to third parties with a focus on real privacy. The trend that Microsoft has succumbed to with Edge was clear in one way or another and the current result in early 2024 is a shattered landscape of bloated web browsing apps once known as “browsers”. Features first, security second - just reverse the order, please!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/microsoft-edge-bug-could-have-enabled-attackers-to-install-malicious-extensions-without-detection/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/microsoft-edge-bug-could-have-enabled-attackers-to-install-malicious-extensions-without-detection/</guid>
                
                <category>security</category>
                
                <category>microsoft</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                <category>internet</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Microsoft adds „</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;with-ai-already-being-more-than-just-the-next-big-thing-it-is-more-than-clear-that-with-great-power-there-comes-great-responsibility-considering-this-the-ultimate-question-whether-ai-should-be-centralized-or-not-is-surely-one-of-the-key-aspects-we-need-to-talk-about-in-the-field-of-artificial-intelligence-now-emad-mostaque-ceo-of-stability-ai-is-resigning-in-the-wake-of-the-current-row-over-this-issue&quot;&gt;With AI already being more than just „the next big thing“, it is more than clear that, with great power, there comes great responsibility. Considering this, the ultimate question whether AI should be centralized or not is surely one of the key aspects we need to talk about in the field of Artificial Intelligence. Now Emad Mostaque, CEO of Stability AI, is resigning in the wake of the current row over this issue.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we go all out and make Terminator’s “Skynet” a reality, the ethical question of how to deal with the power of AI and how to regulate it is omnipresent. With this in mind, Emad Mostaque has &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/EMostaque/status/1771380668930674850&quot;&gt;apparently resigned&lt;/a&gt;, and while Stability AI [has already expressed its regret] (https://stability.ai/news/stabilityai-announcement), Mostaque himself states that he “does not want centralized AI to fight centralized AI”, while still retaining a majority stake in the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/stability_ai_twitter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Twitter statement&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-state-of-ai-in-early-2024&quot;&gt;The state of AI in early 2024&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Mostaque, he is in favour of decentralized AI, talking about the challenge of coordinating and regulating AI rather than making it more powerful. This seems to be in contrast to the models of OpenAI or Anthropic, both of which started out quite open but over time have closed themselves off, making it impossible even to know what kind of data samples were used to train the specific AI models. “Concentration of power is bad for all of us,” says Mostaque, who is already concerned about a “strange focus on revenue” when it comes to AI-focused companies, while believing that AI is still “the biggest tech bubble of all time” that still needs constant research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/Stable+Video+-+Blog+Image+1920x1080+-+2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stability AI artwork&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the power and possibilities of artificial intelligence are imminent, it is still unclear how generative AI can be turned into a stable business based on a specific funding model. Even OpenAI-founder Sam Altman admitted that there is no real idea of how the whole industry can be underpinned by a revenue-based cash flow as the development and deployment of AI-models is currently too expensive to be refinanced by recurring revenues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rumour has it that Stability AI investor Coatue also urged Mostaque to step down, citing a more profit-driven approach to the company. Citing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://stability.ai/news/stabilityai-announcement&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; accompanying his departure, Mostaque says: “I strongly believe in Stability AI’s mission and feel that the company is in the right hands. Now is the time to ensure that AI remains open and decentralised,” followed by a thought that is accompanied by a desire to refocus while preparing the company for its next step in growth. In the wake of recent events, Stability AI is also facing &lt;a href=&quot;https://fingfx.thomsonreuters.com/gfx/legaldocs/byvrlkmwnve/GETTY%20IMAGES%20AI%20LAWSUIT%20complaint.pdf&quot;&gt;legal action from Getty Images&lt;/a&gt; for possible copyright infringement: The company is believed to have used copyrighted material, including the Getty Images logo, to train the AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;still-some-work-to-do&quot;&gt;Still some work to do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While AI is still in its infancy and already offers many opportunities, the ethical questions have yet to be answered. Decentralized or centralized, regulated or unregulated: Although everyone seems to be jumping on the AI bandwagon (and many have already done so), the technology is already involved in our everyday lives and boundaries are hardly set. There is more AI in today’s technology than many of us can imagine, but the models need to be trained with sample data - at least for now: Sample data that not everyone has access to or is allowed to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/SVD+blog+cover+image.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stability AI&quot; /&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are endless use cases and possibilities, but recent events around OpenAI and Sam Altman’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://openai.com/blog/review-completed-altman-brockman-to-continue-to-lead-openai&quot;&gt;temporary leave (and glorious return!)&lt;/a&gt; or Emad Mostaque’s resignation from Stability AI show that there is still much to discuss. Is AI a public good? Should the big tech players be funding and owning a technology that could take us to the stars or doom humanity for all time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no consensus yet, and as Ben Parker once said in Spider-Man: “With great power comes great responsibility” - hopefully we’ll find a way to deal with the enormous power we have in our hands with Artificial Intelligence. Founders or CEOs leaving their companies when the path is bifurcated is an alarm signal and leading a discussion about the use and control of AI is essential - without diminishing the capabilities of modern Artificial Intelligence to fill many gaps!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/stability-ai-loses-ceo-ahead-of-reframing-business-model/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/stability-ai-loses-ceo-ahead-of-reframing-business-model/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>ai</category>
                
                <category>internet</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>How to delete stored credentials from a YubiKey</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-yubikeys-for-securing-accounts-is-a-premium-step-to-a-nearly-ultimative-security-approach-besides-passkeys-or-simple-2fa-alas-over-time-those-hardware-tokens-often-fill-with-more-and-more-accounts---adding-them-is-no-big-deal-but-getting-rid-of-older-entries-isnt-that-intuitive-either-talk-about-in-the-field-of-artificial-intelligence&quot;&gt;Using YubiKeys for securing accounts is a premium step to a nearly ultimative security approach besides Passkeys or „simple“ 2FA. Alas, over time, those hardware tokens often fill with more and more accounts - adding them is no big deal, but getting rid of older entries isn’t that intuitive either. talk about in the field of Artificial Intelligence.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Securing online accounts is one behavioral paradigm I have followed since hardware keys appeared and were affordable. With starting to use a password manager many years ago, also Two-Factor Authentication (2 FA) found its way into this security chain and in the time before the Passkeys (and still today) another layer of security is still mandatory. Paired with complex passwords, each layer helps to protect online accounts and even a password appearing in a new breach doesn’t scare that much if there is another, second (or third) factor helping you to prevent a personal and digital disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I am tending to check and change passwords as well as services mostly in the spring (call it spring cleaning!), I am also checking whether I still use a specific service or not. If not, I try to delete the account - the same procedure applies to accounts residing on my YubiKeys. I don’t add credentials to them every day so I do this phased and then continue to work with the keys for weeks or months - so I simply forget which data is already stored on those hardware tokens. As I am also a friend of cleaning up a historical mess, I try to get rid of old credentials when I don’t need them anymore - something that is quite difficult if you handle the YubiKeys just with the official YubiKey Manager. The app (still no Universal Binary on macOS in 2024) helps you to change many parameters but also prevents you from easily deleting unneeded credentials. This works anyway and, despite quite hidden, is done with the YubiKey Manager CLI - so let me show you how we can accomplish this task on our YubiKeys without resetting the device to factory defaults!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/oliver-hale-oTvU7Zmteic-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cleaning in progress&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-the-yubikey-manager-cli&quot;&gt;Getting the YubiKey Manager CLI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Windows-users, the way of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yubico.com/support/download/yubikey-manager/?ref=pifferi.info&quot;&gt;getting the CLI&lt;/a&gt; is pretty straightforward as it comes bundled with the YubiKey Manager-application and resides in C:\Program Files\Yubico\YubiKey Manager. As long as your YubiKey uses at least firmware 5.2.x, you will instantly be able to deal with it using the CLI as documented &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.yubico.com/software/yubikey/tools/ykman/Using_the_ykman_CLI.html?ref=pifferi.info&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mac-version 1.25 comes as a .PKG-file and obviously misses the CLI so we need to make use of extended package managers like Homebrew to fetch the desired file named „ykman“.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing &lt;a href=&quot;https://brew.sh&quot;&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt; is pretty straightforward but yet another topic so assuming you have already done so by either typing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;/bin/bash -c &quot;$(curl -fsSL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/HEAD/install.sh)&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or using the new and official .PKG-installation for Macs hosted on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Homebrew/brew/releases/latest&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, a simple&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;brew install ykman
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;should do the trick and, after some packages were fetched, we’re finally ready to go on macOS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/yubikey-version.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Checking the proper YubiKey-version&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;doing-the-magic-with-ykman&quot;&gt;Doing the magic with ykman&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having met the one and only prerequisite, ykman is ready to so firing up the command without any specific parameter should show us the following screen with all options available:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/yubikey_ykman_mac.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking what we can do with ykman&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see which credentials are stored, just enter a&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ykman fido credentials list
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;followed by your personal PIN (which should be set, otherwise using a hardware security key is quite pointless).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A list of services will appear, guided by a credential ID:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/ykman_yubikey_services.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking what we can do with ykman&quot; /&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To delete a specific service, simply use the following command followed by the specific credential ID:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ykman fido credentials delete [credential id]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, for removing my apple.com-account from my YubiKey (always two there are!), the appropriate command would be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ykman fido credentials delete d60f8b33
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and it would be just the first entry with credential ID d60f8b33 that would be deleted from the YubiKey’s storage!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To check whether the credentials have been removed or not (believe me, they should!), another&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ykman fido credentials list
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;will show the remaining credentials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;verdict&quot;&gt;Verdict&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With simple materials on board, we have managed to remove single elements and stored credentials from an YubiKey without the need to fully wipe the device. Despite the CLI-tools are quite hidden on Mac or - to be more specific - must be installed separately from the YubiKey Manager, we finally used Homebrew for doing this task for us, enabling us to clean unwanted credentials from out precious YubiKey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/flyd-FGH69mi53Mw-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking what we can do with ykman&quot; /&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way may be quite helpful if you aren’t aware which credentials are stored on the YubiKey and just want to see or delete them on a per-item basis instead of wiping the whole device, forcing you to re-integrate the whole hardware token with each service connected!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/how-to-delete-stored-credentials-from-a-yubikey/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/how-to-delete-stored-credentials-from-a-yubikey/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>security</category>
                
                <category>token</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Spring Cleaning - Tidying up your Mastodon-instance</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;after-six-months-of-running-a-small-two-user-mastodon-instance-i-was-astonished-to-see-the-media-growth-over-the-time-so-it-was-way-overdue-to-reflect-how-to-do-some-spring-cleaning-in-this-cozy-self-hosted-space&quot;&gt;After six months of running a small, two user Mastodon-instance, I was astonished to see the media growth over the time so it was way overdue to reflect how to do some spring cleaning in this cozy, self-hosted space.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite carefully selecting and tuning Mastodon’s internal retention policies to (obviously) suit my needs, I discovered this small instance filling up nearly 1,8 TB of storage in my S3-bucket: Fortunately, I am actively tracking my monthly bills  of my Wasabi-account but considering that, not long ago, a whole TB was enough for some of my Fediverse-based services and some backups in separate buckets, I was forced to get to the bottom of this case and found the Mastodon-based cached media assets to be the root of this evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/mastodon_retention_settings.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mastodon’s retention policies&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mastodons-materials-on-board&quot;&gt;Mastodon’s materials on board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, Mastodon’s backend is indeed some kind of beast so the &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.joinmastodon.org/admin/tootctl/&quot;&gt;built-in CLI&lt;/a&gt; gives you the availability to clean attachments and previews from remote accounts, purging the precious disk cache.  Despite Mastodon having tons of options, you may rarely use them on a daily basis so I did finally spend some time to get used to the single commands. Afterwards, combining and scheduling them on a cron-basis may help you to save valuable disk space, no matter where your data is stored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/mastodon_s3_utilization_before.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mastodon’s space utilization in its S3-bucket&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-script&quot;&gt;The script&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six single commands are the road to our success of re-gaining storage space for our Mastodon-instance. Being the „mastodon“-user on my system and assuming you use the same user and the same paths according to Mastodon’s official guide for deploying your own server, I decided to create an empty file via&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;vi /home/mastodon/mastodon-cleanup.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and filled it with the combination of six commands and the specific explanations aiming at a retention of fourteen days which should, in my case, serve well - feel free to alter these parameters according to your personal needs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;#!/bin/bash

# Prune remote accounts that never interacted with any local user
RAILS_ENV=production /home/mastodon/live/bin/tootctl accounts prune;

# Remove remote statuses that local users never interacted with older than 14 days
RAILS_ENV=production /home/mastodon/live/bin/tootctl statuses remove --days 14;

# Remove media attachments older than 14 days
RAILS_ENV=production /home/mastodon/live/bin/tootctl media remove --days 14;

# Remove all headers (including people you follow)
RAILS_ENV=production /home/mastodon/live/bin/tootctl media remove --remove-headers --include-follows --days 0;

# Remove link previews older than 14 days
RAILS_ENV=production /home/mastodon/live/bin/tootctl preview_cards remove --days 14;

# Remove files not linked to any post
RAILS_ENV=production /home/mastodon/live/bin/tootctl media remove-orphans;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now make the script executable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;chmod +x /home/mastodon/mastodon-cleanup.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve never run these commands before (just as I did) I’d suggest you start with initially running them one by one as they might take several hours or days to run for the first time. The size of the cached media and database will depend on how many people you follow (approximately 100 in my case), how many users are on your specific instance or how many relays you have added to your instance - just to name some aspects. With Mastodon being a federated Social Network, there are many pros but also cons as each server is talking to other ones, gathering lots of data - which lead us to the dilemma of a quite impressive disk space consumption even with a very small instance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;scheduling-time&quot;&gt;Scheduling time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we have initially deployed each of the six single commands and freed up the first batch of space, it is sure that we don’t want to do this manually each time. Fortunately, Linux Cron-daemon is our Swiss Army knife for scheduling and with just a single line of code, our script will run at specific times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as logged in „mastodon“-user, just deploy a&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;crontab -e
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to enter this user’s cron-settings. Now just add another line at the end of the file matching your needs when this script should run. After the first run, it won’t take that much time anymore so I decided that I am fine with running it every six hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;0 */6 * * * /bin/bash /home/mastodon/mastodon-cleanup.sh
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t familiar with the syntax of Cron, I recommend to use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://crontab-generator.org&quot;&gt;Crontab Generator&lt;/a&gt; which is always a good way to to check whether your job is correct or not - or even create the whole command you may insert into the crontab instantly for you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/mastodon_cleanup_crontab_settings.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The crontab-settings&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Save the file and from this moment on, cron will take care of executing the script every six hours!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;verdict&quot;&gt;Verdict&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this small tutorial, we managed to implement a great mechanism of automatically getting rid of cached and material and media on our own Mastodon-instance. This is by far the best-practice for every instance and yes, every file may be download and cached again once we interact with the specific status or message connected to it - therefore this solution is more an approach for smaller instances instead of larger ones but, as always, tastes (and demands) are different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/lia-trevarthen-gWvdUpNQr6g-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dealing with storage boxes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to your type of storage you may see the result quite fast or - in my case - on the next day as Wasabi’s statistics need their time to refresh the bucket size. With local storage, the result should be imminent, for me it took its time but the used space decreased drastically and ended up with Mastodon taking less than only 20 GB afterwards! Especially in terms of Wasabi and even despite the fact that the space is freed up immediately, you even pay for deleted storage for 90 days in advance here - in my case a good compromise to prevent the egress-charges from other S3-providers but this is yet another topic!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, putting all provider-specific considerations aside, this script should help you to control the amount of cached media on your Mastodon-server. Feel free to adopt the script to match your specific needs and do a spring cleaning on your Mastodon-instance - I hope that you somehow consider this post as some kind of useful! And - if you’re interested.  feel free to find my profiles in The Fediverse on&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mastodon - &lt;a href=&quot;https://norse.social/@oliver&quot;&gt;https://norse.social/@oliver&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pixelfed - &lt;a href=&quot;https://pix.norse.social/oliver&quot;&gt;https://pix.norse.social/oliver&lt;/a&gt; and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BookWyrm - &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.norse.social/@oliver&quot;&gt;https://books.norse.social/@oliver&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and let’s follow or connect with each other!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/Spring-Cleaning-Tidying-up-your-Mastodon-instance/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/Spring-Cleaning-Tidying-up-your-Mastodon-instance/</guid>
                
                <category>socialnetwork</category>
                
                <category>mastodon</category>
                
                <category>linux</category>
                
                <category>cron</category>
                
                <category>fediverse</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>My default apps starting 2024</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;there-have-been-many-lovely-events-in-the-internet-over-the-years-and-one-to-cherish-especially-is-the-one-where-users-simply-blog-about-their-favorite-standard-apps-they-are-using&quot;&gt;There have been many lovely events in the Internet over the years and one to cherish especially is the one where users simply blog about their favorite standard apps they are using.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a simply idea and despite reminding me on some kind of classic chain letter, I stumbled upon this campaign by swiping through my Mastodon-feed. Niklas, a lucky German guy who managed to live in Norway (yes, I am definitely jealousy of him here!) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.niklas.fyi/posts/2024-01-11-default-apps/&quot;&gt;shared his list&lt;/a&gt;. After looking what all this was really about, I discovered &lt;a href=&quot;https://rknight.me&quot;&gt;Robb Knight’s&lt;/a&gt; site and his „&lt;a href=&quot;https://defaults.rknight.me&quot;&gt;App Defaults&lt;/a&gt;“-project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, he initiated and collected RSS-feeds people in the Net telling exactly which standard-apps / services they use and although this is a quite basic idea, it is one of the vivid and positive things in the WWW these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;📨 Mail Service: &lt;a href=&quot;http://icloud.com/mail&quot;&gt;iCloud Mail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;📮 Mail Client: &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/app/mail/id1108187098&quot;&gt;Apple Mail&lt;/a&gt; on macOS &amp;amp; iOS, &lt;a href=&quot;http://icloud.com/mail&quot;&gt;iCloud Mail&lt;/a&gt; in the Web&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;📝 Notes: &lt;a href=&quot;https://obsidian.md&quot;&gt;Obsidian&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icloud.com/notes&quot;&gt;Apple Notes&lt;/a&gt; (dying)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;✅ To-Do: &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/reminders/id1108187841&quot;&gt;Apple Reminders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;🌅 Photo library: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icloud.com/photos&quot;&gt;iCloud Photos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;📆 Calendar: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icloud.com/calendar&quot;&gt;iCloud Calendar&lt;/a&gt; CalDAV&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;📁 Cloud Storage: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.synology.com/dsm/feature/drive&quot;&gt;Synology Drive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;📖 RSS Service: Self-hosted &lt;a href=&quot;https://freshrss.org/&quot;&gt;FreshRSS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;🙍🏻‍♂️ Contacts: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icloud.com/contacts&quot;&gt;iCloud Contacts&lt;/a&gt; CardDAV&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;🌐 Browser: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/safari/&quot;&gt;Safari&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ungoogled-software/ungoogled-chromium&quot;&gt;ungoogled-chromium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;💬 Chat: &lt;a href=&quot;https://signal.org/&quot;&gt;Signal&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/zm/app/messages/id1146560473&quot;&gt;Messages&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/threema-the-secure-messenger/id578665578?ign-mpt=uo%3D4&quot;&gt;Threema&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;🛒 Shopping Lists: &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/reminders/id1108187841&quot;&gt;Apple Reminders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;🔎 Search: &lt;a href=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com&quot;&gt;DuckDuckGo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;📚 Reading: Printed (!) books&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;📰 News: &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/app/reeder-5/id1529445840&quot;&gt;Reeder 5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;🎵 Music: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/apple-music/&quot;&gt;Apple Music&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;🎤 Podcasts: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/apple-podcasts/&quot;&gt;Apple Podcasts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;🌤️ Weather: &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/weather/id1069513131&quot;&gt;Apple Weather&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;🔐 Password Management: Self-hosted &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitwarden.com&quot;&gt;Bitwarden&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;🧮 Code Editor: &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/app/coteditor/id1024640650?mt=12&quot;&gt;CotEditor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/dan-cristian-padure-noOXRT9gfQ8-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tools&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As 2024 is still being young but already comes along with uprising political turmoil here in Germany paired with a quite dissatisfied population, there are definitely some more serious things to handle this year. Anyway, it’s quite funny to create this list and look how it will develop over time as needs and use cases may change like they have changed over the years - so apart from the real serious events on this planet, this one here is a welcomed relief…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/My-default-apps-starting-2024/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/My-default-apps-starting-2024/</guid>
                
                <category>internet</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                <category>social</category>
                
                <category>apps</category>
                
                <category>services</category>
                
                
                <category>Software</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Season Greetings and goodbye forever, 2023!</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;it-was-a-special-and-somehow-strange-year---paired-with-many-experiences-and-the-proof-that-there-are-often-unexpected-insights-into-human-nature&quot;&gt;It was a special and somehow strange year - paired with many experiences and the proof that there are often unexpected insights into human nature.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back even into the COVID-years which defined our way the last three years (while the plague is still there), 2023 wasn’t the best year in many ways. It was a year of change, a year of insights and a year of breaking bonds with people seemingly flagged as „friendly co-workers“ just because of a job change: All those experiences finally built their own, full circle and, in the end, other positive outcomes helped to leave the past behind while aiming towards a better personal future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a professional basis, many things changed in its foundation starting this March, &lt;a href=&quot;../The-best-way-to-predict-your-future-is-to-create-it/&quot;&gt;finally enabling me&lt;/a&gt; to leave a dead-end caused by many wrong strategical decisions over the last consecutive three years. Over the year, there was a s&lt;a href=&quot;../Stop-worrying-about-people-that-arent-worried-about-you/&quot;&gt;teep learning curve&lt;/a&gt; experiencing that, during these days, literally leaving the Hogwarts Express heading to anywhere except Hogwarts may leave you disposed into the nowhere. Seen from a business view, you were useful once you opted out continuing to howl with the wolves despite the real wolves in sheep’s closing tried to make anything worse powered by missing awareness, ignorance and ongoing megalomania.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/hadija-9cgMKmZyhH0-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Past or future?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-personal-view&quot;&gt;The personal view&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a personal point of view, it was also challenging year. Seeing how fast your kids - my four girls - grow up is a blazing experience and, deeply felt, this speed is accelerating every single month. We faced an absolutely sad and unexpected loss as my father-in-law suddenly passed away in March, ripping our Italian heart out of our family’s chest. With the pain growing, the family closed ranks even more and while I consider many opportunities to suit better, my brother-in-law lived with us for nearly two weeks, helping is sister and everyone of us to redress the pain. After this, a wonderful week in Denmark was welcomed to create a distance to the awful events and drove me to &lt;a href=&quot;../The-best-way-to-predict-your-future-is-to-create-it/&quot;&gt;make a final decision&lt;/a&gt; on my job perspective, summing everything up with the result being perfectly clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the year, the world seemed to continue to go down the swanny once again: &lt;a href=&quot;../The-only-thing-we-have-to-fear-on-the-planet-is-man/&quot;&gt;Ongoing war in the Ukraine&lt;/a&gt;, a (German) society striving to the far-right regarding politics (while everyone seeing this happen), the state of (worldwide) politics in general and environmental events like the climate change being a threat to all of us not worth discussing: The challenges for mankind are ahead and if rising temperatures, floods, thunderstorms and other events aren’t proof enough that we’re already too late to participate in the game of change, then this planet may indeed be doomed. While politicians still gather their lickspittles around them, deny these threats and continue to curry favour with the fuel-lobby instead of really patronising solar and wind energy-options, many people have realized that we must turn towards new energies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/tania-malrechauffe-Tq7lbAeF9BQ-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Change politics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The clash of culture(s) is preprogrammed and will be an immense task not only for the new year to come as the countdown to extinction (as Megadeth already knew and sung about in 1992) is still ticking… faster. Basically, many nations and governments (not only the German one) need a complete overhaul but where to start? It needs an invest of everyone and so my thoughts since the COVID-19 pandemic were fortified over the years: Every man for himself - a dangerous tendency!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-personal-view-1&quot;&gt;The personal view&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I am quite sure that some debts will be payed off next year and surely many people will encounter the lovely wisdom of „as you sow, so you shall reap“. Karma is a bitch and sometimes it takes longer for people to earn what they were striving for - in the end, everyone finally gets what he deserved. &lt;a href=&quot;../Stop-worrying-about-people-that-arent-worried-about-you/&quot;&gt;I was personally disappointed by a lot of people in 2023&lt;/a&gt; and my (formerly good) knowledge of human nature failed in many ways. But there is hope with an old (and trustworthy) but also new workforce around me, with new people acting in concert and new challenges ahead. Let’s work on and with these, let’s be successful and let’s create a working culture within a promising company really empowering the employees to participate instead of building a castle in the clouds guarded by an unicorn while everyone actually knows that everything is pouring down the sink anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/cristian-escobar-abkEAOjnY0s-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New year&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be familial challenges ahead, challenges with health and my growing kids but I hope that we will somehow manage those in the best-possible ways so staying healthy as long as possible is surely one of the better wishes for an upcoming new year. While this one comes to an end, I try to put many disappointing moments of 2023 into a box, seal and get rid of them. The sad moments prevailed but the good moments are a foundation to build trust on, no matter if it was a 60 km-hike within three days, opening an exciting new chapter of your professional life with ten people in common, playing „Hogwarts Legacy“ with your eldest or conquering the (still-not-real) North of Norway with three wonderful and crazy guys: Hope for the better lives on, so be welcomed, 2024 - and hopefully this year will be a better one than the last ones as the good often comes unexpected!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/season-greetings-and-goodbye-forever-2023/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/season-greetings-and-goodbye-forever-2023/</guid>
                
                <category>life</category>
                
                <category>thoughts</category>
                
                <category>work</category>
                
                <category>christmas</category>
                
                <category>newyear</category>
                
                
                <category>Thoughts</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>New Outlook seemingly sends sensitive data to Microsoft</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;especially-in-it-trust-is-everything-and-working-with-different-solutions-and-providers-is-always-a-matter-of-trust-the-possible-fact-that-microsofts-new-outlook-offshout-is-seemingly-sending-sensitive-data-to-redmond-could-shake-the-world-it-to-its-very-foundations---years-after-the-once-acquired-mobile-outlook-app-did-the-same&quot;&gt;Especially in IT, trust is everything and working with different solutions and providers is always a matter of trust. The possible fact that Microsoft’s new Outlook-offshout is seemingly sending sensitive data to Redmond could shake the world IT to its very foundations - years after the once acquired mobile Outlook-app did the same.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the growing inconsistency of the classic and “new”, often undercooked iterations of Microsoft Desktop-applications (you may have noticed this with Teams and Outlook already), the latest Windows-version seems to be quite keen on submitting IMAP- and SMTP-credentials to Microsoft-servers as German site &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.heise.de/news/Microsoft-krallt-sich-Zugangsdaten-Achtung-vorm-neuen-Outlook-9357691.html&quot;&gt;heise.de&lt;/a&gt; reported this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;everything-new&quot;&gt;Everything “new”?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking highly of the “new Outlook”, &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/outlook-blog/things-to-look-forward-to-in-the-new-outlook-for-windows/ba-p/3975602&quot;&gt;Microsoft’s plan is that this new version is about to replace&lt;/a&gt; the abandoned Windows Mail and the well-known, monolithic desktop client on Windows and macOS. Users can already switch to the new Outlook but while several elemental features (on-premises Exchange-support, PST-support on Mac etc.) are missing, the way Redmond deals with personal information and login credentials is quite questionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/New_Outlook_Welcome.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Microsoft-apps&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2023-Windows 11-update already implements “Outlook (new)” into the start menu under “Recommended apps” so many users may give this a try - but substituting margarine for butter doesn’t always have the effect usually hoped for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/new_outlook_win11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New Outlook deployed within an update&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In detail, adding a new account to the new Outlook which isn’t hosted by Microsoft, a certain reference is given, explaining that “non-Microsoft-accounts are synced with the Microsoft” cloud as stated &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.microsoft.com/de-de/office/synchronisieren-ihres-kontos-in-outlook-mit-der-microsoft-cloud-985f9e19-d308-4e85-9d1d-0c6f32f8e981?ui=de-de&amp;amp;rs=de-de&amp;amp;ad=de&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; in German. At the time of writing, only iCloud-, Gmail-, Yahoo- and general IMAP-accounts and the Microsoft 365-stack are supported (and therefore synced!), including the versions on iOS, Android and macOS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/new_outlook_sync_warning.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Microsoft-apps&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following this notify, adding an IMAP-account to the new Outlook comes equal with syncing E-Mails with Microsofts servers. Existing contacts and calendar-entries won’t get synced but everything what is created in the new Outlook afterwards gets a direct injection into the Microsoft Cloud for whatever reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentioning the note above which things are synced, users may question the intention behind this move. Why does the vendor of my software application not only need to save the credentials for a personal mailbox but also presume to access the personal data of users and sync them with their own systems?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;heise.de was able to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.heise.de/news/Microsoft-lays-hands-on-login-data-Beware-of-the-new-Outlook-9358925.html&quot;&gt;sniff the traffic&lt;/a&gt; between new Outlook and the Microsoft-servers, proving that the output contained the target server, login name and password which were sent to the Microsoft Cloud. Although the connection itself appeared to be TLS-protected, the data was sent to Microsoft in plain text within the tunnel. Without informing or inquiring about this, Microsoft grants itself access to the IMAP-and SMTP login data of users of the new Outlook which is, basically, an undeniable no-go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-now&quot;&gt;What now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, user should sit this deployment out as long as possible. There are enough alternatives around to connect IMAP-accounts with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thunderbird.net/&quot;&gt;Thunderbird&lt;/a&gt; being probably the most-famous one. There can be no reason for Microsoft doing this and while Redmond already caused an outcry years ago when the acquired - now - Outlook Mobile-app did already send credentials to third parties, using this new half-cooked app for whatever reason is an imminent threat for everything at least slightly connected to data protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/matthew-manuel-BhLSBX-0rnM-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Microsoft-apps&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, this is seemingly only affecting IMAP-accounts but as Outlook is also mostly used in the Enterprise, it is more than questionable what Microsoft tries to achieve with this move. I don’t want neither my private mails, calendars and contacts nor my credentials to the accounts hosting those transmitted to the creator of a Personal Information Manager. Considering the latest bad press on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/microsoft/hackers-stole-microsoft-signing-key-from-windows-crash-dump/&quot;&gt;stolen keys&lt;/a&gt; of Microsoft’s cloud infrastructure, this whole thing comes with a very bad taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong, I have used Microsoft-products my whole life and am partially still doing so in private while I have to rely on them in business life - wether I like it or not. But the inconsistency of new software (just switch between the classic and “new” Outlook on Mac) or the undercooked releases (old Teams? New Teams?) just cast long shadows on Redmond’s quality of code and the common alignment of Microsoft as a vendor. Combined with the dreadful firing of new, partially unwanted or unfinished, features or software, a feeble impression comes up that there doesn’t seem to be any common theme except the wild gathering of data for whatsoever reason: This finally matches my personal impressions on the development of Microsoft Edge which started as a great alternative to Chrome but turned to a bloated meeting point of unwanted features over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/new_outlook_bfdi.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;GDPR-issue?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gdpr-calling&quot;&gt;GDPR calling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Federal Commissioner for Data Protection and Freedom of Information of Germany, Professor Ulrich Kelber, is alarmed by the data detour in Microsoft’s new Outlook. On Mastodon he informed about the intention &lt;a href=&quot;https://social.bund.de/@bfdi/111381793883035665&quot;&gt;to ask for a report from the Irish Data Protection Commissioner&lt;/a&gt; who is told to be responsible for companies like Microsoft, during a meeting of the European data protection supervisory authorities next Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, it’s up to us users to answer and react - and for everyone directly in charge of enforcing GDPR-compliances, this may be a new target to definitely aim and focus at and especially businesses should keep Outlook’s journey under review!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/new-outlook-seemingly-sends-sensitive-data-to-microsoft/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/new-outlook-seemingly-sends-sensitive-data-to-microsoft/</guid>
                
                <category>internet</category>
                
                <category>microsoft</category>
                
                <category>security</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                <category>outlook</category>
                
                
                <category>Internet</category>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>