<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Oliver&apos;s Blog</title>
        <description>My own small private space in the world of bewitched madness!</description>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
        <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 13:02:22 +0200</pubDate>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 13:02:22 +0200</lastBuildDate>
        <generator>Jekyll v4.3.3</generator>
        
            <item>
                <title>Microsoft rolls out passkey support for personal Microsoft accounts</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;passkeys-arent-all-that-new-and-many-users-who-subscribe-to-personal-microsoft-365-services-or-use-private-microsoft-accounts-have-been-clamoring-for-this-feature-the-good-its-here-matching-this-years-world-password-day-the-bad-microsoft-is-doing-microsoft-things---again&quot;&gt;Passkeys aren’t all that new and many users who subscribe to personal Microsoft 365 services or use private Microsoft accounts have been clamoring for this feature. The good: It’s here, matching this year’s World Password Day. The bad: Microsoft is doing Microsoft things - again!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.passkeys.com&quot;&gt;Passkeys&lt;/a&gt; are a more secure and easier replacement for passwords. They allow users to log in to applications and websites using a biometric sensor (such as a fingerprint or facial recognition like Windows Hello etc.), PIN or pattern, freeing them from the hassle of remembering and managing passwords. Yesterday I also &lt;a href=&quot;https://pifferi.info/bitwarden-launches-new-mfa-authenticator-app/&quot;&gt;blogged&lt;/a&gt; about the new Bitwarden Authenticator and mechanisms already implemented into the parent Bitwarden Password Manager - including support for passkeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2024/05/02/microsoft-introduces-passkeys-for-consumer-accounts/&quot;&gt;Microsoft is joining the party, finally bringing passkeys to consumer Microsoft 365-accounts&lt;/a&gt;, following in the footsteps of all the other modern services that have already implemented passkeys. Now, users can log in to their Microsoft consumer accounts with a passkey, allowing them to continue to use password-free authentication methods such as Windows Hello, FIDO2 security keys, biometric tools (facial scans or fingerprints) or device PINs to strengthen their layer of security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft further clarifies the term “consumer accounts” to mean personal accounts for access to Microsoft services and products such as Windows, Microsoft 365 including the specific services contained therein, the all-new Copilot and the Xbox Live-services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/microsoft_passkey_roadmap.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Microsoft’s roadmap when it comes to passkeys!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hello-passkeys&quot;&gt;Hello, passkeys&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, passkeys are finally here for Microsoft consumer accounts, and this integration has been long overdue. Passkey support for Microsoft Windows for logging into websites and applications was already available but with the addition of support for Microsoft-led online accounts, consumers can now log in with ease, following the long-announced roadmap to finally ditch passwords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically, passkeys are a variant of a passwordless authentication mechanism that uses a cryptographic key pair. While the public key is stored on the service provider’s server, the private key is securely stored on the user’s device. When the user attempts to authenticate, a challenge is created that requires the private key to solve and confirm the user’s identity. Because the private key is protected by device-level security mechanisms such as PIN or biometrics, the user only needs to provide this information to seamlessly log in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past few months and years, we have already seen the growth of services supporting passphrase authentication and even its deep integration into operating systems or browsers (MacOS / Safari paired with Touch ID) or separate password managers like &lt;a href=&quot;https://pifferi.info/bitwarden-launches-new-mfa-authenticator-app/&quot;&gt;Bitwarden&lt;/a&gt;, which also comes with its OS-independent implementation of passphrase support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-need-to-sync-for-convenience-reasons&quot;&gt;The need to sync for convenience-reasons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passkeys are usually tied to specific devices but with deeper integration into single solutions, there is also an option to sync them and make them available on all devices: Apple did this with the iCloud Keychain (with pros and cons but &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-us/102651&quot;&gt;documented&lt;/a&gt;) and also, for example,  Bitwarden’s sync feature allows users to use passkeys on all devices in use if they are initially configured to do so. On the other hand, you can also add each single device to specific accounts when omitting a sync, for example for security reasons or simply no need to sync at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/arekfurt/status/1786127091550875974&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/microsoft_passkeys_sync_x.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The bad - it syncs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Microsoft wouldn’t be Microsoft these days if the road of good intentions wasn’t paved with some questionable intentions: Redmond also synchronizes passkeys with other connected devices rather than just storing unique passkeys on each device. Technically, this isn’t the most secure method because if an attacker gains access to a particular account, all of the configured passkeys will be synced to that device. According to Microsoft, this decision was made „for reasons of convenience“, allowing people to maintain access to their accounts when upgrading or losing their devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of creating passkeys is fairly straightforward and well documented in &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/account-billing/signing-in-with-a-passkey-09a49a86-ca47-406c-8acc-ed0e3c852c6d&quot;&gt;Microsoft’s official support document&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just follow your device’s instructions on supported systems (Windows 10 and later, macOS Ventura including Safari 16 or later, iOS 16 and later, Chrome/ChromeOS, Microsoft Edge 109 and later or Android 9 and later): When signing in to your Microsoft account, select “Other ways to sign in,” select “Face, fingerprint, PIN, or security key” and then select the passkey you saved earlier from the list or use the OS-specific dialog like this one in Safari on macOS Sonomo 14.4.1 running Safari 17.4.1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/microsoft_passkeys_touchid.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Signing in&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s good to finally see Microsoft adopting passkeys for personal accounts, enhancing the overall layer of security. Seen from a different perspective, „security“ is something that Microsoft is currently struggling with so syncing the passkeys while referring to „convenience“ is something that has a rather foul taste: The foul taste of gathering as much personal information about the user a possible, effectively going the Google-way and without a technical justification how the sync works and how the passkeys are protected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The good:&lt;/strong&gt; Passkeys are finally here for non-business accounts!&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;The bad:&lt;/strong&gt; Microsoft continues to do the Microsoft things of our time while still struggling with security and trust these days, so it would be nice to have some more clarity on the protection of the newly implemented passkeys…&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 05 May 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/microsoft-rolls-out-passkey-support-for-personal-microsoft-accounts/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/microsoft-rolls-out-passkey-support-for-personal-microsoft-accounts/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>microsoft</category>
                
                <category>security</category>
                
                <category>2fa</category>
                
                <category>m365</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Tusks - Make posting to Mastodon feel like posting to a blog</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;sometimes-i-come-across-apps-that-i-would-never-have-missed-apps-that-come-out-of-nowhere-and-still-find-their-niche---tusks-by-developer-bardi-golriz-is-one-of-them-aiming-for-a-new-focus-when-posting-on-mastodon&quot;&gt;Sometimes I come across apps that I would never have missed. Apps that come out of nowhere and still find their niche - Tusks by developer &lt;a href=&quot;https://mas.to/@bardi&quot;&gt;Bardi Golriz&lt;/a&gt; is one of them, aiming for a new focus when posting on Mastodon.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although there are many Mastodon clients out there including my beloved &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/de/app/ivory-for-mastodon-by-tapbots/id6444602274&quot;&gt;Ivory&lt;/a&gt;, Tusks is not intended to replace them. Instead, this clean and slim app tries to complement existing clients by simply focusing on different tasks than the typical “post-a-picture-or-video-stuff-paired-with-some-text“-scenario we know from Social Media these days. &lt;a href=&quot;https://thirdculture.app/tusks&quot;&gt;Tusks&lt;/a&gt; gets rid of the timeline and just shows you your own posts, helping you to focus and build a thread-like experience while keeping everything in order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-tusks-works&quot;&gt;How Tusks works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting a new thread in Tusks is as easy as making a single post but that’s not what makes it special. Tusks actively discourages posting into a vacuum and losing valuable context - this state is achieved by making it effortless to continue threading narratives. Each post becomes an update to a larger story that we can tell. Tusks is clearly aimed at pure writing but also supports the posting of images, including content warnings, and is aimed at people who blog, post or simply want to write more without distraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/tusks_composer.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Composing with Tusks!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tusks shows posts as well as any replies to the original post but users won’t see replies or interactions with others. The app also comes with several features to help you organize and publish such as pinning threads for quick access, ignoring irrelevant posts when searching, or writing as much as possible on the go while Tusks breaks everything down into individual posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/tusks_context_menu.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tusks context menu&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app is currently free and can be downloaded from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/gb/app/tusks-make-mastodon-your-blog/id6473683937&quot;&gt;App Store&lt;/a&gt;. This free version is read-only and requires an update to Tusks Pro for posting and publishing which currently costs $4.99 / €5.99 for the first thousand fans and early adopters. Indie developer &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:bardi.golriz@gmail.com&quot;&gt;Bardi Golriz&lt;/a&gt; also says that the app will have a more expensive LTD (at least $9.99) and possibly a subscription option after the first thousand slots are filled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/tusks_ipad_inbox.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tusk’s iPad Inbox&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-client-client-replacement-or-&quot;&gt;New client, client replacement or… ?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, Tusks is indeed no replacement for any of our standard Mastodon-apps but that’s not the intention here. Indeed  it puts even more value on Mastodon in case you meet the criteria the app was made for - focus, blogging, thread-based tooting. Although the current release is the initial one, the app’s quality is already very fine and stable on all platforms while the &lt;a href=&quot;https://midnight-beanie-ccb.notion.site/281be94b75504b60b600eb73ee1072f9?v=9479d0e4e1e8468187a7e2efbe3a53c7&quot;&gt;official roadmap&lt;/a&gt; already covers even more promising potential like editing posts, drag and drop, multi-account support or even scheduling posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are more of a blogger than a „tootist“ and have struggled with splitting posts into threads (a nightmare if you need to do it manually), you should definitely check out Tusks - you may not have missed it before, but it will certainly improve your tooting experience. It also helps to focus on the essential aspects of working with Mastodon and the topics people like to write about, and in my case, it definitely drives me to automatically work on longer articles that Tusks will publish in the future!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/tusks-make-posting-to-mastodon-feel-like-posting-to-a-blog/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/tusks-make-posting-to-mastodon-feel-like-posting-to-a-blog/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>tusks</category>
                
                <category>mastodon</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                <category>socialnetwork</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Bitwarden launches new MFA authenticator-app</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-use-of-a-second-factor-to-secure-online-accounts-has-become-a-must-over-time-long-before-the-triumph-of-passkeys-although-there-are-already-plenty-of-mobile-apps-that-generate-the-multi-factor-bitwarden-has-decided-to-create-its-own---and-it-has-a-pretty-interesting-roadmap&quot;&gt;The use of a second factor to secure online accounts has become a must over time, long before the triumph of passkeys. Although there are already plenty of mobile apps that generate the multi-factor, Bitwarden has decided to create its own - and it has a pretty interesting roadmap!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, the history of the (more or less) complex password has been a special one and after multi-factor authentication found its way to users, using an application to enter a generated number (the multi-factor) in addition to the password itself was the way to go. Over the years, security approaches have changed and hardware keys and passkeys have been added to the security layer but the first line of defense after a strong and complex password (and the least people can do to secure their accounts) are these randomly generated numbers from password managers or (even better) standalone apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of having at least a second factor at hand was recently demonstrated &lt;a href=&quot;https://pifferi.info/apple-locks-users-out-of-their-apple-ids-without-explanation/&quot;&gt;by the unexpected reset of my Apple ID-connected devices&lt;/a&gt; which forced me to update my password - I was worried, but definitely less worried because 2FA was already enabled in its most extreme iteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/towfiqu-barbhuiya-FnA5pAzqhMM-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Security first!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now Bitwarden has &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitwarden.com/blog/bitwarden-just-launched-a-new-authenticator-app-heres-what-it-means-to-users/&quot;&gt;officially released&lt;/a&gt; a new multi-factor authentication app available for &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/bitwarden-authenticator/id6497335175&quot;&gt;iOS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.bitwarden.authenticator&quot;&gt;Android&lt;/a&gt;. It features the familiar TOTP (time-based one-time passwords) and can be used for accounts by scanning a QR code or manually entering the initial setup key, providing the familiar extra layer of authentication. Bitwarden, being an Open Source project, also provides the code for both apps in public GitHub repositories, separated into Android (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitwarden/authenticator-android&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) and iOS (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bitwarden/authenticator-ios&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;„Bitwarden Authenticator provides immediate value to the Bitwarden user base who has been asking for a standalone app for several years. Stay tuned for upcoming new features that will help enterprise organizations enforce security policies to protect and monitor authentication to business applications.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Kyle Spearrin, founder and CTO of Bitwarden)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/bitwarden_authenicator_setup01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First setup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the TOTP feature was already implemented in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitwarden.com&quot;&gt;Bitwarden Password Manager&lt;/a&gt;, it was a premium add-on only available to paying customers or those using a self-hosted derivative called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dani-garcia/vaultwarden&quot;&gt;Vaultwarden&lt;/a&gt;. So speaking (and assuming this feature is still of interest to users), people can now stay within the “Bitwarden” brand and use the official authenticator, whether they’re paying customers or not. For example, if someone is new to Bitwarden, they can start with this standalone application without having to use Bitwarden’s password vault features, as these applications are (still) separate. From a security perspective, the second factor should usually be separated from the password manager itself, so running both apps could also be an improvement for current users and their own security layer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/bitwarden_authenicator_setup02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Continued setup&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding new accounts is pretty straightforward, either by scanning the QR code or entering the token for the service you want to enable 2FA for. Bitwarden also revealed a guided roadmap with this first release in Phase 1 and not much else to do besides enabling 2FA or exporting the entries in it to a .json-backup file. There is no real backup yet, instead the phone backup will take care of backing up the data stored in the authenticator. An import option is said to be coming soon, and Authenticator codes synchronized with a Bitwarden account are features already announced for Phase 2. Phase 3 will bring push-based 2FA and account recovery as additional features while the final phase will target employee authentication and further &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitwarden.com/help/policies/&quot;&gt;security polices&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/bitwarden_authenticator_roadmap.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bitwarden roadmap&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitwarden Authenticator is a great and free addition to the existing TOTP-supporting applications and although it is still in its early stages, it already has the Bitwarden-flavour that I have loved since discovering it as my preferred password manager. For now, the codes it generates stand on their own without any connection to the password vault itself but with Phase 2 already coming with this feature, the physical separation of two important tools (password manager and 2FA app) based on one database could be yet another improvement for users’ security structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s still some work to be done, but even at this early stage, Bitwarden Authenticator is a great alternative to other apps and assuming you already trust Bitwarden with your password vault (or even host it yourself), why not use this app to refine your Bitwarden-powered security baseline?&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/bitwarden-launches-new-mfa-authenticator-app/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/bitwarden-launches-new-mfa-authenticator-app/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>bitwarden</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                <category>security</category>
                
                <category>2fa</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Apple locks users out of their Apple IDs without explanation</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;security-and-big-tech-are-two-terms-that-dont-go-well-together-at-the-moment-after-ongoing-security-issues-at-microsoft-apple-seems-to-have-at-least-one-minor-problem-that-has-left-many-users-unexpectedly-locked-out-of-icloud-and-devices-belonging-to-it-and-forced-to-perform-an-unexpected-password-change-however-depending-on-apples-forthcoming-response-to-the-case-this-minor-problem-could-turn-into-a-serious-one&quot;&gt;“Security” and “big tech” are two terms that don’t go well together at the moment. After ongoing security issues at Microsoft, Apple seems to have at least one minor problem that has left many users unexpectedly locked out of iCloud and devices belonging to it and forced to perform an unexpected password change. However, depending on Apple’s forthcoming response to the case, this minor problem could turn into a serious one.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a simple day with your beloved Apple devices - to be honest, this is the status quo on pretty much every day. This Friday, I first noticed that my Apple Watch Ultra was unable to update the weather forecast and the current temperature. I had arrived at one of our offices early and was therefore not in a „trusted location“ - which are my home address and the nearest office, my main place of work. Suddenly I noticed that the Apple Watch was forcing me to verify the password of my Apple account (an old @mac.com one) out of nowhere. Then my iPhone came along with the same effect - feeling that something was very strange, I tried to access Apple’s [account page] (https://appleid.apple.com/) and discovered that my account was indeed locked, forcing me to recover it with a subsequent password change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/apple-id-down.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Apple ID down?&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that I am a bit of a “tinfoil-hat” guy, as friends and colleagues call me, when it comes to security, I tried to find out what could be wrong. I haven’t added any new devices to my account, which is of course protected by 2FA, backed up by two YubiKey 5C NFC keys. iOS 17.3’s “Stolen Device Protection” is also enabled, and at the time of writing I was not using any applications that require an application password - which got deleted after the account reset by the way! The password I used for my beloved old @mac.com address is generated and definitely not something that could be guessed or brute-forced - the tinfoil-hat guy, remember?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I reset my password, knowing that I had some work to do at home later that evening. Two hours later, the same messages appeared again on my iPhone and Watch, so I went through the same process, feeling that something had to be wrong - and fearing that my account had some kind of security issue, especially since Apple’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/support/systemstatus/&quot;&gt;official status page&lt;/a&gt; didn’t show anything unusual. Anyway, with all the security options Apple provides, the likelihood of a security flaw should be quite low - but the issue concerned me anyway (and should concern anyone with a similar experience). So, maybe it was a technical issue or something that forced Apple to lock my account?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/apple_id.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Apple-devices&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, many people began reporting similar incidents around the world - many of them focusing on old @mac.com or @me.com addresses in the context of being the head of a family using the Family Sharing feature on iCloud.com. 9to5mac.com &lt;a href=&quot;https://9to5mac.com/2024/04/26/signed-out-of-apple-id-account-problem-password/&quot;&gt;reported the issue&lt;/a&gt; fairly early on and staff at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/daveywinder/2024/04/27/apple-id-password-reset-issue-hitting-iphone-ipad-and-macbook-users/&quot;&gt;Forbes&lt;/a&gt; had similar experiences. Also &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2024/4/27/24142509/apple-id-logged-out-reset-stolen-device-protection&quot;&gt;The Verge got in line&lt;/a&gt; as well. The good news: I was not the only one. The bad: Nobody knew what was really going on because something was definitely wrong but Apple refused to comment on the issue, drawing the familiar veil of silence over the incident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, the Net has been flooded with news about the issue, so the whole thing seems to have a greater impact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://theinternet.social/@tbridge/112340463598872085&quot;&gt;Thread #1 on Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://eworld.social/@ismh/112340745553157794&quot;&gt;Thread #2 on Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mastodon.social/@ChrisLawley/112340853972099137&quot;&gt;Thread #3 on Mastodon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michael Tsai’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://mjtsai.com/blog/2024/04/26/janky-apple-id-security/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@singletary/post/C6P9jfJt1VH&quot;&gt;Threads #1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@andelirich/post/C6P88QiNY-J&quot;&gt;Threads #2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@adhdjesse/post/C6P9hS_L9_7&quot;&gt;Threads #3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@9six7/post/C6P-cP1sNu7&quot;&gt;Threads #4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@jubnub/post/C6P_DNyMVaT&quot;&gt;Threads #5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@timmeh71/post/C6P_b4prnWJ&quot;&gt;Threads #6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@ngorby/post/C6PvqnArUpZ&quot;&gt;Threads #7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.threads.net/@nichagan/post/C6Pzb8jLrvx&quot;&gt;More complaints on Threads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next-apple&quot;&gt;What’s next, Apple?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, among my friends and acquaintances, I was the only one affected - the only one with an “old” @mac.com-Apple ID. There was also no reaction in our family to similar effects (at least no one was texting or calling, so everything seems to be working). As The Net reports, Apple is downplaying the problem in terms of support calls and is not saying anything specific about “why” the whole thing happened in the first place. Personally, I could live with any explanation (precaution? attack? technical glitch?), as my security baseline is definitely more than just the simple standard, using all the options each vendor (in this case Apple) offers me but definitely there should be an official statement on this issue that has not just affected a few individual users. There is no need to diminish the relative importance of this case, and simply saying nothing is the wrong way to prove that “security” and “privacy” are still at the heart of Apple’s agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/igor-son-Nod1nQ0i5a0-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Apple-devices&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, we see that security is not a status quo, but an ongoing process. Vendor agnostic. It’s a process often paved with good intentions and a lot of backtracking, but it’s never finished. For every measure there is a countermeasure, and yes, I love Apple, my fenced (and falling down) garden and the products that grow in it (and are paid for by the users) but specifically in this frustrating and annoying case I want an answer - and I am not alone!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So even as (or because being!) a loyal Apple fan and user for two decades, I have to ask the obvious question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you have to say about that, Apple?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/apple-locks-users-out-of-their-apple-ids-without-explanation/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/apple-locks-users-out-of-their-apple-ids-without-explanation/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>apple</category>
                
                <category>security</category>
                
                <category>2fa</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Microsoft adds recommended apps to the start menu in Windows 11</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;microsoft-is-currently-battling-a-lot-of-bad-press-but-as-if-that-wasnt-enough-theres-still-something-else-to-add-according-to-a-recent-blog-post-the-latest-windows-11-insider-preview-build-226353495-will-add-recommended-apps-to-the-users-start-menu---at-least-in-the-us-and-on-unmanaged-devices&quot;&gt;Microsoft is currently battling a lot of bad press but as if that wasn’t enough, there’s still something else to add: According to a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.windows.com/windows-insider/2024/04/12/announcing-windows-11-insider-preview-build-22635-3495-beta-channel/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;, the latest Windows 11 Insider Preview Build 22635.3495 will add recommended apps to the user’s start menu - at least in the US and on unmanaged devices.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this is only a test in a preview version of Windows 11, it is yet another ticked box on the list of foreign intrusion into the user’s operating system that is sadly part of Microsoft’s recent history. The unwanted &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2020/10/19/21524006/microsoft-pause-unsolicited-pwa-office-app-windows-10&quot;&gt;progressive web apps (PWAs) in Windows 10&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pifferi.info/new-outlook-seemingly-sends-sensitive-data-to-microsoft/&quot;&gt;privacy issue with the ‘new’ Outlook sending credentials to Redmond servers&lt;/a&gt; or this new issue raises the question of whether the installed operating system belongs to the user or is subject to Microsoft’s arbitrariness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/bekky-bekks-QRHRqOVOcfQ-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ads ahead!&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, and whenever I have to deal with a client’s Windows system, I have never got used to the new “features” of grouping recently installed applications or showing frequently installed applications. This may have something to do with my own past when the classic Start menu had everything I needed. This was later superseded by these new features and in present days, whenever I have to deal with a Windows system, the combination of the Windows key and the ‘S’ is far quicker than any new idea from Redmond associated with the Start menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, as if that wasn’t enough already, the latest obvious idea is to recommend fancy and famous applications from the Microsoft Store in the Start menu even if you’ve never had a relationship with them. So, Redmond, what could possibly go wrong with this great new addition of useless bloatware to an operating system, cloaking this under the smoke screen of friendly recommendations to explore new, yet unknown apps?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/start-reco-1password.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A Microsoft genuine idea&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely this could just be another test balloon, with Redmond experimenting with new features that may (and hopefully) never make it to the final build. It’s also stated that only US-users enrolled in the Windows Insider program will be able to see this change and that it won’t apply to commercial devices (“devices managed by organizations”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we have become accustomed to, these friendly recommendations can also be turned off by going to „Settings &amp;gt; Personalization &amp;gt; Start“ and unchecking the „Show recommendations for tips, app promotions and more“-box. Unfortunately they seem to be standard in this build and users will have to turn this feature off in the same way they can prevent the Start menu from showing frequently installed or used apps - once they made their way throughout the dazzling and confusing new system settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a reminder, we regularly try out new experiences and concepts that may never get released with Windows Insiders to get feedback. Should you see this experience on the Start menu, let us know what you think. We are beginning to roll this out to a small set of Insiders in the Beta Channel at first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-do-you-want-to-go-tomorrow-microsoft&quot;&gt;Where do you want to go tomorrow, Microsoft?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the phrase “it’s not a bug, it’s a feature”? It just popped into my head when I thought of those friendly additions to a simple operating system. Seemingly, Redmond lost its way on the desktop many years ago and while the focus is clearly on the cloud and the bundle of services that reside there, the desktop is somehow losing its historic role and adding pointless features to an end-user operating system may be one of the few facts that justify a new press release with leading the users to believe that there is an active development. There aren’t many features that justified ditching Windows 7 for Windows 10, and - in my humble opinion - there were even fewer that justified ditching Windows 10 in favour of Windows 11 and whatever may come. The desktop got boring and there aren’t that much justifications to slip creepy features to working operating systems without the user’s permission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the days of extraordinary changes on the desktop are over and operating systems are pretty mature - the same trend applies to my beloved macOS (at least for my use cases and personal needs). Instead of blowing these systems up, the focus should be on stripping them down to the bare essentials - with people being able to install the features they need, when they need them! The current trend coming out of Redmond is simply awful, and even if this is just a test in a preview version of Windows 11, the trend is clear - and the mistakes are being repeated over time. While the cloud is referred to as “just other people’s computers”, how do we ensure that using the latest iteration of Windows leaves us in control of our own PCs in the future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking of this, where do you want to go tomorrow, Microsoft?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/marcus-urbenz-hPA60HpZUrI-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A Microsoft genuine idea&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/microsoft-adds-recommended-apps-to-the-start-menu-in-windows-11/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/microsoft-adds-recommended-apps-to-the-start-menu-in-windows-11/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>microsoft</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                <category>windows</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>German state of Schleswig-Holstein bets on digital sovereignty for the modern workplace</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-open-source-strategy-in-german-states-and-municipalities-is-not-that-common-while-the-idea-of-decoupling-those-scopes-from-big-tech-isnt-that-new-just-remind-the-city-of-munichs-failed-linux-project-back-in-2017-reality-is-telling-yet-another-story-now-the-german-state-of-schleswig-holstein-has-recently-announced-a-new-workplace-strategy-based-on-digital-sovereignty&quot;&gt;An Open Source-strategy in German states and municipalities is not that common. While the idea of decoupling those scopes from Big Tech isn’t that new (just remind the city of Munich’s failed „Linux“-project back in 2017!), reality is telling yet another story. Now, the German state of Schleswig-Holstein has recently announced a new workplace strategy based on digital sovereignty.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just “Schleswig-Holstein against the trend”, it’s a statement that contains a lot of potential, but also the well-known sceptical thoughts about whether Linux and Open Source in general are able to replace Microsoft &amp;amp; Co. in public and governmental institutions. Call it “pioneering work”, but the realisation of this &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schleswig-holstein.de/DE/landesregierung/ministerien-behoerden/I/_startseite/Artikel2024/II/240403_digitalsouveraene_verwaltung.html&quot;&gt;roadmap&lt;/a&gt; could indeed provide a real example that there can be a change in dependency if only every single sub-item on this long list of prerequisites can be marked as “checked”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-announcement&quot;&gt;The announcement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Einstieg in den Umstieg” is the slogan chosen by Schleswig-Holstein for the official announcement, meaning “entry into the change” - which says it all. While it’s not unusual for someone to try to switch from proprietary software to FOSS-based software, the fact that a German state has officially expressed this yearning for change is quite a groundbreaking proclamation, turning away from Big Tech-backed software (here) in the form of Microsoft-solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/schleswig_holstein.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hello, Schleswig-Holstein&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the banner of “independent, sustainable, secure”, Schleswig-Holstein wants to lead the way while being the first German state to introduce the modern workplace based on digital sovereignty in local government. Following a decision by the cabinet, the widespread adoption of LibreOffice as the standard office suite is just the first step and the starting point for a broader strategy aimed at complete digital sovereignty in the state of Schleswig-Holstein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;„The future of government is cloud-based, automated, algorithmic and data-driven. Therefore, all our future applications will be cloud-based. However, we don’t have any control over how data is processed, nor do we have any control over any data leakage.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Dirk Schrödter, Minister of Digitalization)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;„Our responsibility to the citizens of our state is to ensure that every single piece of data is kept secure and that we are always in control of the IT solutions we implement. Securing digital sovereignty is at least as important as securing power and energy sovereignty.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/christian-lue-8Yw6tsB8tnc-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Europe first&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;focusing-on-europe&quot;&gt;Focusing on Europe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dirk Schrödter also names the focus on Europe as one of the key factors for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schleswig-holstein.de/DE/landesregierung/ministerien-behoerden/I/Presse/PI/2024/CdS/240403_cds_it-arbeitsplatz.html?nn=549a8fa0-66c0-4da0-9f19-70e4be245eac&quot;&gt;new and pioneering digital strategy of Schleswig-Holstein&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;„The path to digital sovereignty follows a strict industrial policy compass: My vision of a strong digital garrison can only become a reality if we don’t have to invest our public budgets in licensing costs.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cabinet’s decision marks the start of the transition from proprietary software to free, Open Source-based solutions for some 30,000 users in the administration. Proprietary software refers to digital applications that are strictly limited in terms of copyright, licensing and further processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;„Instead, we can invest it in local digital companies and create local value and jobs. Our goals in developing a common digital single market are interconnected digital government solutions and services. As a government, we use the potential of data to create and secure innovation, value chains and wealth at home.“&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/dirk_schroeter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dirk Schrödter&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, these offerings are usually tied to data centre- or managed services which ultimately allows the product owner to retain sovereignty over these products and services - so breaking these dependencies is ultimately key to Schleswig-Holstein’s ongoing and future-based digital strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-factors&quot;&gt;The factors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s right, there are not seven pillars of wisdom, as T. E. Lawrence once wrote but only six, all of which are part of the digital sovereign workplace in the state of Schleswig-Holstein:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Replacement of Microsoft Office with LibreOffice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changing the basic OS from Microsoft Windows to Linux&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collaboration within the state administration and external parties: Using Open Source-solutions Nextcloud, Open Xchange/Thunderbird paired with Univention AD-Connector superseding Microsoft Sharepoint and Microsoft Exchange/Outlook&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A new approach with an Open Source-based directory service taking over from Microsoft Active Directory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inventory of the single specific procedures in terms of compatibility and interoperability with LibreOffice and Linux&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Development of an Open Source-related telephony solution replacing Telekom-Flexport&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All six together are said to provide a solid foundation for the digital challenges ahead. By switching to open source, Schleswig-Holstein is laying the foundations for creating, maintaining and preserving digital sovereignty. Pros such as increased IT security, efficiency, data protection and seamless cooperation between different software systems are cited as well as the goal of making future development results in the Open Source-sector available to the “greater whole” under the rights of free software licensing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to forget: Any change requires proper change management and with such a high turnover, user adoption is inevitable and a single beam carries the whole project: The use of LibreOffice for communication between departments and authorities is to be implemented in the short term, with exceptions in case the switch cannot be made for technical or professional reasons. According to Schleswig-Holstein there is already a wide range of training available for employees which will be expanded as needed. What’s more, the state’s central IT administration is making skilled staff available to ensure that user acceptance is not a showstopper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-two-cents&quot;&gt;My two cents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This step is a big signal. Despite the amount of work that still lies ahead for the IT administration of Schleswig-Holstein, this announcement and all its consequences could be THE initiator for the decoupling of old status quos that have always relied on Microsoft solutions. There is a use case for everything but considering the current dependencies and even pure facts in terms of security (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/microsoft-still-unsure-how-hackers-stole-msa-key-in-2023-exchange-attack/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cisa.gov/sites/default/files/2024-04/CSRB_Review_of_the_Summer_2023_MEO_Intrusion_Final_508c.pdf&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;), there should be an alternative to Big Tech - at least if the reappraisal of this whole bunch of unfortunate events within the attack chain is so sloppy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/shahadat-rahman-BfrQnKBulYQ-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Embracing Open Source&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this transition will take time - it certainly will - and the path of good intentions will be paved with delays, frustrations and other obstacles. On the other hand, the ultimate goal of creating digital sovereignty for an entire German state will be within reach, setting a good example for others to follow. Turning away from Microsoft-based solutions may be a sacrilege from many points of view, but there are alternatives to proprietary software - so if this project turns out to be a success (with the planned FOSS-based solutions, as advised), Schleswig-Holstein may iron out the manifestly bad experiences of Munich’s failed Linux migration which was ended back in 2017. Being independent of possible lobbying, turning to Open Source and contributing experience and code back to the community would be a shining example for other states (do you hear me, North Rhine-Westphalia?) to follow - or even whole governments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ball has been kicked into play and we may be eager to see the result - sometimes all it takes is an open mind, a courageous attitude and the ultimate will to keep going, even if the wind is blowing against you. The cold wind may turn into a vicious storm, but the visual signals are set to ‘Go’, so thumbs up and help from all quarters should be the least we can do to contribute to the cause!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/german-state-of-schleswig-holstein-bets-on-digital-sovereignty-for-the-modern-workplace/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/german-state-of-schleswig-holstein-bets-on-digital-sovereignty-for-the-modern-workplace/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>workplace</category>
                
                <category>opensource</category>
                
                <category>foss</category>
                
                <category>linux</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Was macht eine gute Backup-Strategie aus? Der World Backup Day 2024</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;am-heutigen-31-märz-ist-world-backup-day-wie-es-sich-gehört-und-mittlerweile-moderne-tradition-ist-benötigen-wir-einen-speziellen-tag-um-auf-ein-wichtiges-thema-nachhaltig-aufmerksam-zu-machen-der-world-backup-day-soll-erneut-an-die-bedeutung-von-datensicherungen--und-sicherheit-erinnern&quot;&gt;Am heutigen 31. März ist &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldbackupday.com/en&quot;&gt;World Backup Day&lt;/a&gt;. Wie es sich gehört und mittlerweile moderne Tradition ist, benötigen wir einen speziellen Tag, um auf ein wichtiges Thema nachhaltig aufmerksam zu machen. Der World Backup Day soll erneut an die Bedeutung von Datensicherungen- und Sicherheit erinnern.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In einem Zeitalter, wo das Sichern der eigenen Daten eine Selbstverständlichkeit darstellt und das Gefährdungspotential stetig ansteigt, muss das reine Backup nur ein Teil der gesamten Strategie sein. Doch was macht eine gute Backup-Strategie aus?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;die-historie&quot;&gt;Die Historie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Der frühere Idealweg wurde durch die „3-2-1“-Regel definiert: Drei Backups auf zwei verschiedenen Medientypen und einer Kopie außer Haus - doch selbst das war und (leider auch) ist bei weitem nicht die Regel. Die Realität sieht oft anders aus - ein Backup auf ein Network Attached Storage im selben Raum mag prinzipiell ein Backup sein, eine Strategie steht dahinter aber eher weniger. Diese Denkweise findet man teilweise noch in kleineren Unternehmen, wo ein Backup samt verläßlicher (und ergo oft kostenpflichtiger) Software eher ein „notwendiges Übel“ darstellt. Recovery Tests werden mäßig bis gar nicht durchgeführt, ein Monitoring des Backups geschieht per se sowieso nicht und nach einem dedizierten Sicherung-Konzept braucht man dann eher auch nicht fragen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/chris-yates-iqELIpzpARI-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s World Backup Day - again&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In dem Moment, wo ein zeitlicher Ausfall (aus welchen Gründen auch immer) geschieht, die Uhr klar gegen das Unternehmen tickt und die Faktoren RTO und RPO unbarmherzig in den Fokus rücken, wird schnell klar, dass auch beim Backup eine Strategie unerläßlich und - ja! - lebenswichtig ist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;der-zeit-faktor&quot;&gt;Der Zeit-Faktor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zur Erklärung: Das Recovery Point Objective (RPO) bezieht sich im Allgemeinen auf die Berechnung der Menge an Datenverlusten, die ein Unternehmen innerhalb eines für sein Geschäft relevanten Zeitraums erleiden kann, bevor ein signifikanter Schaden entsteht - und zwar vom Zeitpunkt eines Störungsereignisses bis zur letzten Datensicherung. Redet man also über eine Strategie, so muss man auch zwangsläufig über diesen Faktor reden, der durchaus die erste Risikoklassifizierung darstellt. Die Wiederherstellungszeit (Recovery Time Objective, RTO) wiederum bezieht sich generell auf die Zeit, die eine Anwendung, ein System oder ein Prozess ausfallen kann, ohne dass ein erheblicher Schaden für das Unternehmen entsteht.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/nathan-dumlao-LPRrEJU2GbQ-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s World Backup Day - again&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ebenso steht sie in Verbindung mit der Zeit, die für die Wiederherstellung der Anwendung und ihrer Daten benötigt wird, um den normalen Geschäftsbetrieb nach einem schwerwiegenden Vorfall wieder aufzunehmen: Aus Erfahrung tickt im Worst Case die Uhr gnadenlos gegen die Betroffenen und das eine Backup mag die Daten enthalten, die Rücksicherung dauert aber quälend lange. Sofern also etwas passiert ist, sollte man sich nicht erst dann Gedanken über den Faktor „Zeit“ machen müssen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;die-strategie&quot;&gt;Die Strategie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hat man bereits über RTO und RPO gesprochen, so spricht man unweigerlich auch über das Backup-Konzept, die Mittel (Hard- wie Software) und am Ende eben über die gesamte Strategie: Ein Backup-Server gehört nicht in eine Active Directory-Domäne und er sollte idealerweise auch keinen virtueller Server auf der eigentlich zu sichernden Umgebung darstellen. Idealerweise ist er auch physisch getrennt von den Produktivsystem - ebenso wie die weiteren Repositories, die die Backups enthalten, beispielsweise in einem anderen, unabdingbaren Brandabschnitt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/mark-fletcher-brown-nN5L5GXKFz8-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s World Backup Day - again&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auch die 3-2-1-Regel ist längst nicht mehr der Weisheit letzter Schluß, wie es bereits Veeam seit einiger Zeit beschreibt. Sie wird durch die 3-2-1-1-0-Regel abgelöst, die der Hersteller auch als „goldene Regel“ tituliert: Vorhalten dreier Kopien-/Backups der Daten, Sicherung dieser Backups auf zwei verschiedene Medientypen, Erstellung mindestens einer Offsite- sowie einer Offline-Kopie (Stichwort „Medientrennung“) und die finale „0“ in Form der Verifizierung der getätigten Backups ohne jeglichen Fehler: Das klingt komplex, ist es aber nicht, wenn man seinen Daten entsprechende Priorität einräumt, die Pflichten, Rechte wie auch Risiken in Bezug auf Backups klassifiziert und die richtigen Partner und Dienste an seiner Seite weiß.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ein-vorläufiges-fazit&quot;&gt;Ein (vorläufiges) Fazit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ein Produkt macht noch keine Lösung. Ein Backup noch keine Strategie. Sicherungs-Software, die mit dem „Weiter-Weiter-Fertig“-Installationsweg deployed wird, ist trotz eines möglichen ersten vollständigen Backups weit entfernt von einem wasserdichten Konzept. Das Tape ist (gerade in großen Umgebungen) immer noch nicht tot: Fragen Sie einmal &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibm.com/tape-storage&quot;&gt;IBM&lt;/a&gt;! Ein Restore sollte nur erfolgen, wenn das Backup Ransomware-frei ist: &lt;a href=&quot;https://community.veeam.com/blogs-and-podcasts-57/ransomware-proof-backups-configuring-and-integrating-object-first-with-veeam-vbr-6930&quot;&gt;Veeam&lt;/a&gt; zeigt, wie das funktionieren kann! Ein (selbstverständlich selbst) verschlüsseltes Backup auszulagern, kann mit Bordmitteln auch zu einem vertrauenswürdigen Cloud Service Provider, beispielsweise in die &lt;a href=&quot;https://enthus.de/services-xaas/xaas/enthus-cloud&quot;&gt;enthus Cloud&lt;/a&gt;, erfolgen - und wer am Ende auch noch ein Disaster Recovery-Ansatz erfolgt, wird hier ebenfalls fündig: Zusammen mit der &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hpe.com/de/de/storage/data-protection-solutions/disaster-recovery-zerto.html&quot;&gt;Zerto&lt;/a&gt; von &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hpe.com/de/de/storage/data-protection-solutions/disaster-recovery-zerto.html&quot;&gt;HPE&lt;/a&gt; lassen sich Backups und DRaaS wunderbar gemeinsam betreiben und die Ausfallsicherheit je nach Anforderungen nahezu gen Null fahren!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/wbd_horizontal-date.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It’s World Backup Day - again&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Das sind nur einige Möglichkeiten, derer man im Rahmen dieses jährlich wiederkehrenden World Backups Day „gedenkt“. Eine allgemeine, für jeden Anwendungsfall geltende, Backup-Strategie gibt es nicht. Primär muss verstanden werden, dass vieles, was wir heute als „Backup“ definieren, kein wirkliches ist respektive von einer Backup-Strategie weit entfernt ist. Am Ende kommt es auf das geschärfte Bewusstsein in einer voller Bedrohungslagen gespickten Zeit, die passenden Werkzeuge und Partner an - und auf ein Konzept, dass individuell für den eigenen Use Case zugeschnitten ist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dieses Konzept sollte nicht starr sein, sondern dynamisch an die Möglichkeiten des Marktes und vor allem den eigenen, wechselnden Anforderungen angepasst werden - denn so, wie sich Softwarekomponenten, Partnerlandschaften und Hardware ändern, ändern sich auch die eigenen Anforderungen häufiger, als man es glauben mag. All das zusammen zählt auf eine gute Backup-Strategie ein und hilft auch, künftigen Herausforderungen gelassener entgegenzutreten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In diesem Sinne einen happy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.worldbackupday.com/en&quot;&gt;World Backup Day 2024&lt;/a&gt; und frohe Ostern!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/was-macht-eine-gute-backup-strategie-aus-der-world-backup-day-2024/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/was-macht-eine-gute-backup-strategie-aus-der-world-backup-day-2024/</guid>
                
                <category>backup</category>
                
                <category>strategy</category>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>security</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Microsoft Edge bug could have enabled attackers to install malicious extensions without detection</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;years-ago-i-took-my-first-steps-on-the-internet-with-netscape-navigator-today-browsers-serve-more-than-just-as-a-gateway-to-the-world-wide-web-they-are-essential-software-for-many-purposes-in-our-digital-world-but-also-a-surface-for-modern-attacks&quot;&gt;Years ago, I took my first steps on the internet with Netscape Navigator. Today, browsers serve more than just as a gateway to the World Wide Web. They are essential software for many purposes in our digital world but also a surface for modern attacks.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I prefer to use Safari and Firefox for personal browsing and keep my browsers free of excessive extensions, the situation is different in my business setting. Due to its seamless integration with Microsoft 365 and its underlying services, Edge is the preferred browser here. Although the Chromium-based browser was initially a promising alternative to Google’s Chrome in 2019, it has since become burdened with unnecessary integrations and privacy concerns, both for private users and businesses. Unfortunately, Edge has become quite similar to Google Chrome over time but with a Redmond flavor and a recently reported, serious security issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/microsoft_edge_attack_chain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Attack chain&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-has-happened&quot;&gt;What has happened?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehackernews.com&quot;&gt;The Hacker News&lt;/a&gt; has recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://thehackernews.com/2024/03/microsoft-edge-bug-could-have-allowed.html&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt;, a now-patched security flaw in the browser’s engine could have been abused to install arbitrary extensions on users’ systems and carry out malicious actions in the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This flaw could have allowed an attacker to exploit a private API, initially intended for marketing purposes, to covertly install additional browser extensions with broad permissions without the user’s knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Oleg Zaytsev, security researcher from Guardio Labs)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zaytsev reported an issue with „&lt;a href=&quot;https://labs.guard.io/cve-2024-21388-microsoft-edges-marketing-api-exploited-for-covert-extension-installation-879fe5ad35ca&quot;&gt;Microsoft Edge’s Marketing API being exploited for covert extension installation&lt;/a&gt;“ which was tracked as &lt;a href=&quot;https://msrc.microsoft.com/update-guide/vulnerability/CVE-2024-21388&quot;&gt;CVE-2024-21388&lt;/a&gt; with a CVSS score of 6.5. Microsoft addressed the issue in Edge’s stable versions 121.0.2277.83 released on January 25, 2024, following responsible disclosure in November 2023. Both Zaytsev and Jun Kokatsu were credited by Redmond for reporting this severe exploit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An attacker who successfully exploited this vulnerability could gain the privileges needed to install an extension&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Microsoft said in an advisory for the flaw, also adding it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;could lead to a browser sandbox escape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;technical-details-of-the-case&quot;&gt;Technical details of the case&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically naming it a privilege escalation flaw, Redmond also emphasizes that a successful exploitation of the bug requires an attacker to “take additional actions prior to exploitation to prepare the target environment.” Thus spoken, this is no „exploit in the wild“ but a not-that-unimportant surface attack nevertheless. According to Guardio’s research, &lt;a href=&quot;https://msrc.microsoft.com/update-guide/vulnerability/CVE-2024-21388&quot;&gt;CVE-2024-21388&lt;/a&gt; also enables a malicious actor to install any extensions from the Edge Add-On store without requiring the user’s explicit consent or interaction. This can be done by running JavaScript on bing.com (well…) or on any of the numerous microsoft.com-pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/microsoft_edge_type_of_validation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Type of validation in MS Edge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technically, the browser can install an add-on from the vendor’s own extension marketplace because it has privileged access to certain private APIs. One such APIs in the Chromium-based Edge browser is „edgeMarketingPagePrivate“ which is accessible from a set of allowlisted websites that belong to Microsoft, including bing.com, microsoft.com, microsoftedgewelcome.microsoft.com and microsoftedgetips.microsoft.com - just to name a few!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The API also packs in a method called installTheme() that, as the name implies, is designed to install a theme from the Edge Add-ons store by passing a unique theme identifier (“themeId”) and its manifest file as input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As an added bonus, as this extension installation is not done quite in the manner it was originally designed for, there will be no need for any interaction or consent from the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, an attacker could use CVE-2024-21388 to publish a seemingly harmless extension to the add-ons store and inject malicious JavaScript code into bing.com or other allowed sites. This would allow them to install an arbitrary extension of their choice by invoking the API using the extension identifier. In other words: If the specially crafted extension is executed on the Edge-browser and the user visits, for example, bing.com, the targeted extension will be installed without their consent and the malicious payload can be deployed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/microsoft_edge_extension_installation.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Extension installation in MS Edge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guardio Labs reported that although there is no evidence of this bug being exploited in the wild, it highlights the need to balance user convenience and security. Browser customizations can inadvertently defeat security mechanisms and introduce several new attack vectors in areas a simple browsing user would never expect them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s relatively easy for attackers to trick users into installing an extension that appears harmless, not realizing it serves as the initial step in a more complex attack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zaytsev said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This vulnerability could be exploited to facilitate the installation of additional extensions, potentially for monetary gain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-opinion&quot;&gt;Final opinion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, and in my personal opinion, Edge has become the same monolith that Chrome already is. When it first appeared in 2019 and rose from the ashes of the inglorious first Edge browser, I was more than happy that there was a modern, supported and actively maintained browser with the Chromium engine without the Google bloatware and bad stuff lurking under the surface. Edge’s evolution over the past two years has already seen the changing times, and with many useless features, new (and even more useless) sidebars, and lots of Redmond reporting stuff under the hood, it is more than obvious that Microsoft has lost the essence of being an alternative to Google Chrome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no security by design, and security is not a status quo, but an ongoing process. This also applies to modern browsers, but with more and more features added to a simple browser (with tracking capabilities and framing in the M365 microcosm), Edge has reached the same level as Google Chrome - it just depends on the users whether they are connected to the Google or Microsoft world. Of course, there are many alternatives (did anyone say „&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ungoogled-software/ungoogled-chromium&quot;&gt;ungoogled-chromium&lt;/a&gt;“?), but considering the evolution of browsers over the years, there are not many positive aspects left if you just want to browse the web without built-in trackers, crypto stuff or other fancy crap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There should be a feature freeze (or reduction) coupled with a rethinking of what a browser should basically do for home users, businesses, and people who just don’t want their data exposed to third parties with a focus on real privacy. The trend that Microsoft has succumbed to with Edge was clear in one way or another and the current result in early 2024 is a shattered landscape of bloated web browsing apps once known as “browsers”. Features first, security second - just reverse the order, please!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/microsoft-edge-bug-could-have-enabled-attackers-to-install-malicious-extensions-without-detection/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/microsoft-edge-bug-could-have-enabled-attackers-to-install-malicious-extensions-without-detection/</guid>
                
                <category>security</category>
                
                <category>microsoft</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                <category>internet</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>Stability AI loses CEO ahead of reframing business model</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;with-ai-already-being-more-than-just-the-next-big-thing-it-is-more-than-clear-that-with-great-power-there-comes-great-responsibility-considering-this-the-ultimate-question-whether-ai-should-be-centralized-or-not-is-surely-one-of-the-key-aspects-we-need-to-talk-about-in-the-field-of-artificial-intelligence-now-emad-mostaque-ceo-of-stability-ai-is-resigning-in-the-wake-of-the-current-row-over-this-issue&quot;&gt;With AI already being more than just „the next big thing“, it is more than clear that, with great power, there comes great responsibility. Considering this, the ultimate question whether AI should be centralized or not is surely one of the key aspects we need to talk about in the field of Artificial Intelligence. Now Emad Mostaque, CEO of Stability AI, is resigning in the wake of the current row over this issue.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we go all out and make Terminator’s “Skynet” a reality, the ethical question of how to deal with the power of AI and how to regulate it is omnipresent. With this in mind, Emad Mostaque has &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/EMostaque/status/1771380668930674850&quot;&gt;apparently resigned&lt;/a&gt;, and while Stability AI [has already expressed its regret] (https://stability.ai/news/stabilityai-announcement), Mostaque himself states that he “does not want centralized AI to fight centralized AI”, while still retaining a majority stake in the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/stability_ai_twitter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Twitter statement&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-state-of-ai-in-early-2024&quot;&gt;The state of AI in early 2024&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Mostaque, he is in favour of decentralized AI, talking about the challenge of coordinating and regulating AI rather than making it more powerful. This seems to be in contrast to the models of OpenAI or Anthropic, both of which started out quite open but over time have closed themselves off, making it impossible even to know what kind of data samples were used to train the specific AI models. “Concentration of power is bad for all of us,” says Mostaque, who is already concerned about a “strange focus on revenue” when it comes to AI-focused companies, while believing that AI is still “the biggest tech bubble of all time” that still needs constant research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/Stable+Video+-+Blog+Image+1920x1080+-+2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stability AI artwork&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the power and possibilities of artificial intelligence are imminent, it is still unclear how generative AI can be turned into a stable business based on a specific funding model. Even OpenAI-founder Sam Altman admitted that there is no real idea of how the whole industry can be underpinned by a revenue-based cash flow as the development and deployment of AI-models is currently too expensive to be refinanced by recurring revenues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rumour has it that Stability AI investor Coatue also urged Mostaque to step down, citing a more profit-driven approach to the company. Citing the &lt;a href=&quot;https://stability.ai/news/stabilityai-announcement&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; accompanying his departure, Mostaque says: “I strongly believe in Stability AI’s mission and feel that the company is in the right hands. Now is the time to ensure that AI remains open and decentralised,” followed by a thought that is accompanied by a desire to refocus while preparing the company for its next step in growth. In the wake of recent events, Stability AI is also facing &lt;a href=&quot;https://fingfx.thomsonreuters.com/gfx/legaldocs/byvrlkmwnve/GETTY%20IMAGES%20AI%20LAWSUIT%20complaint.pdf&quot;&gt;legal action from Getty Images&lt;/a&gt; for possible copyright infringement: The company is believed to have used copyrighted material, including the Getty Images logo, to train the AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;still-some-work-to-do&quot;&gt;Still some work to do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While AI is still in its infancy and already offers many opportunities, the ethical questions have yet to be answered. Decentralized or centralized, regulated or unregulated: Although everyone seems to be jumping on the AI bandwagon (and many have already done so), the technology is already involved in our everyday lives and boundaries are hardly set. There is more AI in today’s technology than many of us can imagine, but the models need to be trained with sample data - at least for now: Sample data that not everyone has access to or is allowed to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/SVD+blog+cover+image.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Stability AI&quot; /&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are endless use cases and possibilities, but recent events around OpenAI and Sam Altman’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://openai.com/blog/review-completed-altman-brockman-to-continue-to-lead-openai&quot;&gt;temporary leave (and glorious return!)&lt;/a&gt; or Emad Mostaque’s resignation from Stability AI show that there is still much to discuss. Is AI a public good? Should the big tech players be funding and owning a technology that could take us to the stars or doom humanity for all time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no consensus yet, and as Ben Parker once said in Spider-Man: “With great power comes great responsibility” - hopefully we’ll find a way to deal with the enormous power we have in our hands with Artificial Intelligence. Founders or CEOs leaving their companies when the path is bifurcated is an alarm signal and leading a discussion about the use and control of AI is essential - without diminishing the capabilities of modern Artificial Intelligence to fill many gaps!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/stability-ai-loses-ceo-ahead-of-reframing-business-model/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/stability-ai-loses-ceo-ahead-of-reframing-business-model/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>ai</category>
                
                <category>internet</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                <title>How to delete stored credentials from a YubiKey</title>
                <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-yubikeys-for-securing-accounts-is-a-premium-step-to-a-nearly-ultimative-security-approach-besides-passkeys-or-simple-2fa-alas-over-time-those-hardware-tokens-often-fill-with-more-and-more-accounts---adding-them-is-no-big-deal-but-getting-rid-of-older-entries-isnt-that-intuitive-either-talk-about-in-the-field-of-artificial-intelligence&quot;&gt;Using YubiKeys for securing accounts is a premium step to a nearly ultimative security approach besides Passkeys or „simple“ 2FA. Alas, over time, those hardware tokens often fill with more and more accounts - adding them is no big deal, but getting rid of older entries isn’t that intuitive either. talk about in the field of Artificial Intelligence.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Securing online accounts is one behavioral paradigm I have followed since hardware keys appeared and were affordable. With starting to use a password manager many years ago, also Two-Factor Authentication (2 FA) found its way into this security chain and in the time before the Passkeys (and still today) another layer of security is still mandatory. Paired with complex passwords, each layer helps to protect online accounts and even a password appearing in a new breach doesn’t scare that much if there is another, second (or third) factor helping you to prevent a personal and digital disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I am tending to check and change passwords as well as services mostly in the spring (call it spring cleaning!), I am also checking whether I still use a specific service or not. If not, I try to delete the account - the same procedure applies to accounts residing on my YubiKeys. I don’t add credentials to them every day so I do this phased and then continue to work with the keys for weeks or months - so I simply forget which data is already stored on those hardware tokens. As I am also a friend of cleaning up a historical mess, I try to get rid of old credentials when I don’t need them anymore - something that is quite difficult if you handle the YubiKeys just with the official YubiKey Manager. The app (still no Universal Binary on macOS in 2024) helps you to change many parameters but also prevents you from easily deleting unneeded credentials. This works anyway and, despite quite hidden, is done with the YubiKey Manager CLI - so let me show you how we can accomplish this task on our YubiKeys without resetting the device to factory defaults!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/oliver-hale-oTvU7Zmteic-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cleaning in progress&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-the-yubikey-manager-cli&quot;&gt;Getting the YubiKey Manager CLI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Windows-users, the way of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yubico.com/support/download/yubikey-manager/?ref=pifferi.info&quot;&gt;getting the CLI&lt;/a&gt; is pretty straightforward as it comes bundled with the YubiKey Manager-application and resides in C:\Program Files\Yubico\YubiKey Manager. As long as your YubiKey uses at least firmware 5.2.x, you will instantly be able to deal with it using the CLI as documented &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.yubico.com/software/yubikey/tools/ykman/Using_the_ykman_CLI.html?ref=pifferi.info&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mac-version 1.25 comes as a .PKG-file and obviously misses the CLI so we need to make use of extended package managers like Homebrew to fetch the desired file named „ykman“.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing &lt;a href=&quot;https://brew.sh&quot;&gt;Homebrew&lt;/a&gt; is pretty straightforward but yet another topic so assuming you have already done so by either typing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;/bin/bash -c &quot;$(curl -fsSL https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Homebrew/install/HEAD/install.sh)&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or using the new and official .PKG-installation for Macs hosted on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Homebrew/brew/releases/latest&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, a simple&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;brew install ykman
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;should do the trick and, after some packages were fetched, we’re finally ready to go on macOS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/yubikey-version.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Checking the proper YubiKey-version&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;doing-the-magic-with-ykman&quot;&gt;Doing the magic with ykman&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After having met the one and only prerequisite, ykman is ready to so firing up the command without any specific parameter should show us the following screen with all options available:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/yubikey_ykman_mac.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking what we can do with ykman&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see which credentials are stored, just enter a&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ykman fido credentials list
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;followed by your personal PIN (which should be set, otherwise using a hardware security key is quite pointless).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A list of services will appear, guided by a credential ID:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/ykman_yubikey_services.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking what we can do with ykman&quot; /&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To delete a specific service, simply use the following command followed by the specific credential ID:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ykman fido credentials delete [credential id]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, for removing my apple.com-account from my YubiKey (always two there are!), the appropriate command would be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ykman fido credentials delete d60f8b33
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and it would be just the first entry with credential ID d60f8b33 that would be deleted from the YubiKey’s storage!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To check whether the credentials have been removed or not (believe me, they should!), another&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ykman fido credentials list
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;will show the remaining credentials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;verdict&quot;&gt;Verdict&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With simple materials on board, we have managed to remove single elements and stored credentials from an YubiKey without the need to fully wipe the device. Despite the CLI-tools are quite hidden on Mac or - to be more specific - must be installed separately from the YubiKey Manager, we finally used Homebrew for doing this task for us, enabling us to clean unwanted credentials from out precious YubiKey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../images/flyd-FGH69mi53Mw-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking what we can do with ykman&quot; /&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way may be quite helpful if you aren’t aware which credentials are stored on the YubiKey and just want to see or delete them on a per-item basis instead of wiping the whole device, forcing you to re-integrate the whole hardware token with each service connected!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
                <link>http://localhost:4000/how-to-delete-stored-credentials-from-a-yubikey/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/how-to-delete-stored-credentials-from-a-yubikey/</guid>
                
                <category>it</category>
                
                <category>security</category>
                
                <category>token</category>
                
                <category>software</category>
                
                
                <category>IT</category>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>